<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The principles of the Papists by which their leaders put them upon bloody and treacherous practices, plainly demonstrated by the Scriptures to be most erroneous and wicked. And a few better principles briefly laid down, for them (or others) to meditate on, tending to a peaceable life among men, &amp;c. And also a few quæries left them last of all, to satisfie their consciences in. Partly for the sakes of those among them whose consciences have some tenderness in them, and are not quite feared: partly also for those who through ignorance are too much inclining to them. Also there may be some service of these things to others. By a lover of truth, mercifulness, plain-heartedness, humility and fidelity, W. T.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2157:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The principles of the Papists by which their leaders put them upon bloody and treacherous practices, plainly demonstrated by the Scriptures to be most erroneous and wicked. And a few better principles briefly laid down, for them (or others) to meditate on, tending to a peaceable life among men, &amp;c. And also a few quæries left them last of all, to satisfie their consciences in. Partly for the sakes of those among them whose consciences have some tenderness in them, and are not quite feared: partly also for those who through ignorance are too much inclining to them. Also there may be some service of these things to others. By a lover of truth, mercifulness, plain-heartedness, humility and fidelity, W. T.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 98, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for, and sold by Benjamin Clark, in George-yard in Lombard-street, stationer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" is signed: William Tomlinson.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRINCIPLES OF THE PAPISTS, By which their Leaders put them upon bloody and treacherous Practices, plainly demonſtrated by the Scriptures to be moſt erroneous and wicked. And a few better Principles briefly laid down, for them (or others) to meditate on, tending to a peaceable Life among Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo a few Quaeries left them laſt of all, to ſatisfie their Conſciences in. Partly for the ſakes of thoſe among them whoſe Conſciences have ſome ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs in them, and are not quite ſeared: Partly alſo for thoſe who through ignorance are too much incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them. Alſo there may be ſome ſervice of theſe things to others. By a Lover of Truth, Mercifulneſs, Plain-heartedneſs, Humility and Fidelity, <hi>W. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Every one that doth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved. But he that doth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifest that they are wrought in God,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Jo. 3.20, 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Benjamin Clark,</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> Stationer. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:2"/>
            <head>A PREMONITION TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have fully exprest my ſenſe, who they are that by me are comprehended in this Treatiſe, where I ſpeak to the fourth Principle following. But lest that ſhould not be ſufficiently minded, I have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed the ſame in effect; namely, That by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> or the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Train, or <hi>Pope</hi>'s Children, and ſuch like expreſſions, I do not underſtand the whole Body of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or every individual among them, but the Leading Ruling part, who over-top and over-rule all, in carrying on miſchievous Plots and Deſigns, and thoſe who walk after, or give their aſſiſtance and conſent to ſuch Leaders, and own thoſe Principles hereafter expreſt. If there be any among them that conſent not thereunto, they are not comprehended in this Treatiſe: And
<pb facs="tcp:37495:3"/>ſuch I hope God hath among them; for I do believe, that God hath <hi>a People</hi> even in <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> otherwiſe I ſhall not underſtand what that means, where he ſaith, <hi>Come out of her my people, leſt ye partake of her ſins, and that ye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor do I write theſe things following, in bitterneſs and envy againſt thoſe evil workers, that are acted on to ſuch wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but (though I may uſe ſharpneſs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, yet) it is to open their eyes to ſee what they do, that they may repent of ſuch their evils, and incline their hearts to better things. And therefore writing nothing againſt them in emnity, or ſcurrilous light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but in ſincerity, and a weighty ſenſe of truth, my Conſcience gives me the boldneſs in the Lord, to own what I have written with my Name, leaving the event to the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Tomlinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37495:3"/>
            <head>The Principles of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> by which their Leaders put them upon bloody and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Practices.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THAT the Pope is ſubſtituted by Chriſt, as the Head of his Church upon Earth, and his Vicar, and <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, and ſo hath power to rule the Church, and all ought to be ſubject to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is in his place infallible.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he hath power to forgive People their ſins.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof he is Head, is the only true Church, (namely the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> ſo call'd) and all others that depart from them are Hereticks.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That out of the Church (that is, out of their Church) is no Salvation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That Faith is not to be kept with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That it is no ſin to kill Hereticks; or at leaſt wiſe it ſhall not be imputed to them as a ſin, but rather is a meritorious work to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37495:4"/>them, ſo it be for the advantage of their Church.</p>
            <p>That they are led by theſe Principles, their Actions make ſo manifeſt to all men, that we need not produce their Authors or Writers for them.</p>
            <p>Now I confeſs if I were a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and made fully to believe theſe things, I know not what I ſhould ſtick at, and not venture upon, to obtain an everlaſting Inheritance, and Glory thereby in Heaven for ever. Therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but pity them who are bred up in theſe Principles, and ſo miſled by them; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially becauſe,</p>
            <p>To theſe their Principles two great Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks are added, to guard and defend them, and ſo to bind their People to themſelves thereby, leſt they ſhould depart from them.</p>
            <p>One is, Their bloody and cruel Practices, which indeed ſpring naturally from ſuch bloody Principles.</p>
            <p>The other is, The taking away the Key of Knowledge from People, and keeping them in ignorance: For Thieves and Robbers, and Lyars and Murderers, hate nothing more than the light, becauſe that diſcovers them, and their wicked deeds.</p>
            <p>With what brevity I can I ſhall diſcover the erroneouſneſs, rottenneſs and falſhood, of theſe their Principles, together with the wickedneſs and danger of them, and of their Practices according to them.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37495:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt, That the Pope is ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted as the Head of the Church of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and his Vicar, and <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, and ſo hath power to rule the Church, and all ought to be ſubject to him.</p>
            <p>To this I ſay firſt, If it be overthrown, all the reſt will tumble down with it; for it is the Baſis or Foundation of all the reſt, upon which they ſtand, and alſo the Top ſtone that binds all their Building together. And as <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> of <hi>Gath</hi> headed the Army of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> as their great Champion, whom little <hi>David</hi> brought down groveling to the ground, with a ſmooth ſtone ſlung at his Forehead, and ſo the whole Army was ſcattered: So is the Pope the great Champion, heading <hi>this People of Blood,</hi> his <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> and if he be brought down, the reſt muſt of neceſſity be ſcattered, as having no ſtandard to repair to. I ſpeak not of a particular Pope, as this man, but of that power he arrogates to himſelf, and others attribute to him, and of him whoever he be, that ſtands inveſted therewith. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with a few Arguments againſt him: And the firſt is taken from his pretended Rock, even from <hi>Peter,</hi> whom they ſo much boaſt of; and it is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 1. If the Pope be found in the ſtate and condition of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> for which he was rejected by <hi>Peter,</hi> from having any part or lot in that matter of diſpenſing the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37495:5"/>ſpiritual Gifts of God, then is he not the Head of Chriſt's Church upon Earth, nor his Vicar, nor <hi>Peter</hi>'s lawful Succeſſor, nor hath he any part or lot in diſpenſing the ſpiritual Gifts of God. And this I preſume no body will deny, that hath any common ſenſe or reaſon in them; becauſe they may as well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was once the Head thereof, as one that is in his caſe and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But that the Pope is ſuch a one, I prove thus; Becauſe the ſame carnal mind is fully in the Pope which was in <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> for which he was rejected by <hi>Peter,</hi> from having any part or lot in this matter of diſpenſing the ſpiritual Gifts of God.</p>
            <p>For the manifeſt proof of this, let us take notice what it was that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected for. See that plainly expreſſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. I will therefore ſet down the very words at large, and then take my Obſervation from them. The words are theſe: <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>And when Simon ſaw, that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands, the holy Ghoſt was given, he offered them money.</hi> Ver. 19. <hi>Saying, Give me alſo this power, that on whomſoever I lay hands, he may receive the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Ver. 20. <hi>But Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaid unto him, Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the Gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi> Ver. 21. <hi>Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37495:5"/>heart is not right in the fight of God.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>Repent therefore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> Ver. 23. <hi>For I perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi> Theſe are the words of the Text: From whence it is eaſie for any to take this Obſervation with me, That the only thing wherewith <hi>Peter</hi> charged <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> as the only cauſe of his ſo ſevere ſentence againſt him, and the only thing whereby the carnality and wickedneſs of his heart was diſcovered to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> was this, namely, <hi>That he thought that the gift of God might be purchaſed with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> nothing more is objected againſt <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> And this thought of his heart (which was hereby diſcovered, namely, by offering money) is twice mentioned againſt him, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 20. and 22. <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money. Thou haſt neither part nor lot in this matter, for thy heart is not right in the ſight of God. Repent therefore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thy heart may be forgiven thee.</hi> Thus <hi>Peter</hi> named that thought of his heart twice to him, and nothing but that, whereby he perceived that he was in the gall of bitterneſs, and bond of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Well, But what's this to the Pope, may ſome ſay?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37495:6"/>
            <p>I Anſwer, If he be found having the ſame thought of heart with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> for which alone he was rejected by <hi>Peter,</hi> and under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vore judgement by him, then he is alſo in the ſame condemnation, and hath neither part nor lot in this matter of diſpenſing the ſpiritual gifts of God, but is in the gall of bitterneſs, and bond of iniquity, and his heart is not right in the ſight of God, and ſo he is far off from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt's Vicar, and <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>If my one conſent not to this, then let them ſhew a reaſon why he ſhould not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſome ſentence and judgement, ſeeing he is in the ſame ſtate of wickedneſs, and in the ſame evil thought of heart. Do not think that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake raſhly or unadviſedly, when he pronounced ſuch a ſentence againſt ſuch a wickedneſs, but in that ſpirit that paſſes the ſame ſentence upon the ſame wickedneſs or evil thought, where it ſhall be found; for God is no reſpecter of perſons.</p>
            <p>But if this be granted, (which indeed can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied by any that hath reaſon) That if the Pope be in the ſame evil thought of heart with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> then he muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame ſentence with him. Yet ſome may ſtick here, and ſay thus:</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>The Pope is a Chriſtian, and</hi> Simon Magus <hi>was a Sorcerer, and we cannot imagine him to have ſuch a carnal and evil thought in him as that Sorcerer had.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37495:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To that I ſay, firſt, That <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was as much a Chriſtian as the Pope is, when <hi>Peter</hi> ſo rejected him, and excluded him from having part or lot in this matter: For he was baptized, and continued with <hi>Philip,</hi> and wondred, beholding the Miracles and Signs which were done, as it's expreſſed in the 13th. Verſe of this 8th. Chapter of the <hi>Acts; Then Simon himſelf believed alſo, and when he was baptized he continued with Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whatever <hi>Simon</hi> was or had been, though he was a Sorcerer, yet <hi>Peter</hi> took no notice of that to him, but only of that thought of his heart, that the gift of God may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with money.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But now the main Objection follows, which is this; But how doth it appear that the Pope hath any ſuch thought, namely, that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this his Practice makes Anſwer: Becauſe he ſells the Pardons of ſins and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies for money, and makes his people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that theſe gifts of God may be purchaſed with money; yea, Pardons are ſold and bought for certain prices, and at certain times, from the Popes Agents, who are imployed in that Work. And this was the firſt thing againſt which <hi>Luther</hi> appeared ſo openly, when he began to break off from Popery, being griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſtirred up with zeal, againſt that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37495:7"/>prophaneneſs of the Pope's Agents, who went about preaching up the ſale of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgencies and Pardons for money, and ſo abuſing the holy gifts of God for filthy lucre. This was under Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10th. and by his appointment, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1517. <hi>Polydor. Virgil. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. The like was done by <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th. 17 years before that: But it's needleſs to prove a thing ſo common and manifeſt. Therefore none need doubt of this, that the Pope hath the ſame thought with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> viz. <hi>That the gift of God, even this ſpiritual gift of God, may be purchaſed with money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any one be ſo far tranſported with zeal for their Pope, that they will ſtill affirm, that the Pope hath not ſo wicked a thought as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> in thinking that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money, then by ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him, they make him ſtill worſe, for they make him the greateſt Deceiver in the World, in ſetting that to ſale for money, which he thinks cannot be purchaſed with money. And look to it you <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> whether it be ſo or no; for which of theſe twain ſoever he is found in, you who buy Pardons and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of him, you are cheated both of your money, and of the thing you expect for it: For if he verily thinks that the gift of God, the pardon of ſin, may be purchaſed with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then is he where <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37495:7"/>cannot give you that; and if he have not that thought of heart, he is a Deceiver, and cheats you to fill his own coffers, and ſo both ways you fall ſhort of your hope. Therefore leave him, and humble your ſelves before the Lord, and ſeek the pardon of your ſins from him, and break off your ſins by repentance, and turning to the Lord with your whole heart, and he will be gracious and merciful unto you, and forgive your iniquities. But to buy a liberty of ſinning to your ſelves, is moſt abominable, and looks as if you would ſet the Lord's righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgements againſt ſin at defiance, and betake your ſelves for ſhelter to a corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful man, who had need to repent and pray God, that the thought of his own heart may be forgiven him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument</hi> 2. I come now to a ſecond Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Pope, and to ſhew that he is no true Succeſſor to <hi>Peter;</hi> which I prove by ſhewing, that he is not of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſpiritual ſeed, which of neceſſity every one muſt be, that ſucceeds either <hi>Peter,</hi> or any of the holy Apoſtles of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>To make this clear, let us take notice of theſe two things: 1. What manner of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion is cut off. 2. What manner of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion doth remain.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What manner of Succeſſion is cut off. There was a Succeſſion once which was lineal in the ſame ſeed outwardly; and ſo from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37495:8"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> to Chriſt they ſucceeded one another, as the Son ſucceeds the Father: But this was cut off, as the Scripture plainly ſheweth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28 29. <hi>For he is not a Jew which is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly—but he is a Jew which is one inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. <hi>The Children of Promiſe are counted for the ſeed.</hi> So alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7. <hi>They which are of faith, the ſame are the Children of Abraham.</hi> And again, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the cutting off of the <hi>Jews</hi> through their unbelief, ſhews, that we who are of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> are grafted in into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſtock only by faith, and ſo by faith we ſtand. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Well, becauſe of unbelief they were broken off, and thou ſtandeſt by faith, be not high-minded but fear.</hi> So then you ſee, that outward ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s line was cut off through unbelief. Hence I argue thus, If God hath laid aſide that outward ſucceſſion in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s line, who was called the Friend of God, he will not take up any outward ſucceſſion again to entail his promiſes upon; and if ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion be cut off from that natural ſeed, for want of faith, then all outward ſucceſſion, as from place, or any other outward thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, will not hold where true faith is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but will fail him that depends upon it, as well as it failed the <hi>Jews.</hi> So then whoſoever pretends a ſucceſſion in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeed, (without which he cannot be a Succeſſor to <hi>Peter</hi>) he muſt eſtabliſh his Succeſſion in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37495:8"/>thing, than either in an outward ſeed or in place, or any ſuch like outward thing.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſecondly, let us now take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice, what manner of Succeſſion that is which abides, and wherein that is eſtabliſhed, which makes one a Succeſſor in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> This doth not ſtand in any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing, but in that faith which follows the ſteps of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Rom. 4.11, 12. Faith was reckoned to <hi>Abraham</hi> for righteouſneſs before he was circumciſed, (as the foregoing words do ſhew) <hi>That he might be the Father of all them that believe, though they be not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, that righteouſneſs might be imported unto them: And the Father of Circumciſion, to them who are not of the Circumciſion only, but alſo walk in the ſteps of that faith of our Father Abraham, which he had being yet uncircumeſſed.</hi> Here you may ſee plainly, who are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children now, and ſo Chriſt's, namely, they that walk in the ſteps of that faith of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham,</hi> and they only: For it's ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Thou ſtandeſt by faith, he not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded but fear.</hi> Ver. 21. <hi>For if God ſpared not the natural branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>Behold therefore the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſeverity of God, on them which fell, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, but towards thee goodneſs, if thou conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in his goodneſs, otherwiſe thou alſo ſhalt be cut off.</hi> So here you may ſee it's plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, what cuts a man off from the ſeed of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37495:9"/>
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo from Chriſt; and alſo what eſtabliſhes him in that ſeed: It is walking in the ſteps of that faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in the goodneſs of God, that eſtabliſhes a man; and he that continues not therein, ſhall be cut off.</p>
            <p>Now examine and apply theſe things to the Pope. Doth he walk in the ſteps of the faith of <hi>Abraham?</hi> Surely his works loudly proclaim the contrary. If ye were the Children of <hi>Abraham, ye would do the works of Abraham,</hi> ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.39, &amp;c. <hi>But now ye ſeek to kill me,</hi> this did not <hi>Abraham. Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the luſts of your Father ye will do. He was a Murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth.</hi> That the Pope is in this murthering ſpirit, many Nations have felt it, and the Earth rings of it. How many Maſſacres, how many bloody and inhumane Butcheries have been acted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him? How many private Murders, and ſecret Conſpiracies, to deſtroy mens Lives? How many ſtabbings and poiſonings of perſons of all degrees, many Countreys can witneſs. Is this to walk in the ſteps of the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham?</hi> Is this to continue in the goodneſs of God, who lets his Sun ſhine on the good and on the bad, and ſends rain on the juſt and on the unjuſt?</p>
            <p>The Pope doth hereby clearly manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to be cut off from walking in the ſteps
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37495:9"/>of the faith of <hi>Abraham;</hi> for thus did not <hi>Abraham.</hi> Or doth he continue in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, who walks in the ſteps of him that was a murderer from the beginning? I deſire you poor captiv'd Souls to conſider it, who are under his yoke, and deceive not your ſelves in truſting to him; for you may plainly ſee by his works, what Spirit your Pope is ingrafted into, namely, into his Spirit, who was a murderer from the beginning, and not into his Spirit, who came not to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave. They who have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s faith, and ſo into Chriſt the true ſeed, were never ſuch murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and bloody creatures, but merciful and tender-hearted. Nay, if we go no further than the common Body of the Proteſtants, they never were ſo bloody to you, as your Pope hath taught you to be to them. When did they commit any ſuch Maſſacres upon you, (though you have highly provoked them) as you have done to them, even without provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation? And ſtill you hold on to attempt the like, and repent not of your wickedneſs; which ſhews plainly, that they have more of the true ſpirit and faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> among them than you have; and you partake more of the ſpirit of him that was a murderer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which is infuſed into you, with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that you ſuck in from your Pope and his Church.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37495:10"/>
            <p>I will tell you who your Pope is by the fruits he brings forth; <hi>He is a great Agent of that Apollyon,</hi> that is, Deſtroyer, ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. Who is King over them that have power to hurt men, and he is the outward head of that myſtery of iniquity which was to ariſe; and you cannot find another like him, to act ſuch horrid wickedneſs, and yet under the pretence of Chriſtianity, as if Chriſt, that innocent Lamb of God, (who came not to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave) were now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Patron to devouring Wolves. Here is the myſtery of wickedneſs, ſhrowding it ſelf under the pretence of Chriſtianity; but the Lord will pluck off his vizzard from off his face, and let people ſee, that no murderer hath any inheritance in the Kingdom of God. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15. <hi>No murderer hath eternal life abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. it's ſaid, <hi>The fearful and unbelieving, and the abominable and murderers, and whoremongers, and ſorcerers, and idolaters, and all lyars, ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone.</hi> Again <hi>Ch.</hi> 22. it's ſaid, <hi>Without are dogs and ſorcerers, and whoremongers and murderers, and idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye.</hi> All theſe you ſee are without; they are not within, neither in the Kingdom of Chriſt, nor in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor of the true Body of Chriſt, which is his Church. Theſe very ſins actually cut them off; <hi>If thou continue not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37495:10"/>in his goodneſs, thou alſo ſhalt be cut off,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. So they that are ſuch, they actually cut off themſelves, there needs no other teſtimony againſt them, than the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of their own evil deeds. Pray conſider a little you that are Papiſts, and give me leave to reaſon the caſe with you, who are led by this man of ſin into ſuch abominations. Will the diſguiſe of a Name ſtand you in ſtead, when God ſhall judge the World in righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt? Will it ſerve your turn to ſay, We were called Chriſtians by thy Name? Will not he ſay for all that, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not, ye workers of iniquity?</hi> What will the Name of Chriſtians do you good, if you be not found in his nature, but in a quite contrary nature, doing the will and work of him that was a murderer and lyar from the beginning? What! Chriſtians in Name, and Murderers in Nature? and think that the Name or your Pope will bear you out, when the righteous Judge ſhall judge every man according to the things done in the body, whether good or bad, and when his all-piercing eye ſhall ſearch and judge the ſecrets of all hearts. I aver, that neither he nor you that obey his will in bloody Murders and Maſſacres, are Chriſtians further than in Name, any more than the perſecuting <hi>Jews</hi> were the true and ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> They were of their Father the Devil, <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>as our Saviour told them) becauſe they had
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37495:11"/>murder in their hearts; and are not you of the ſame Father, who have murders, and ſuch horrid murders too, not only in your hearts, but alſo in ſome of your hands? How will you excuſe your ſelves in the day of the Lord's Vengeance, when he ſhall make inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for blood? Will it ſerve you to ſay then, We did as we were inſtructed, and put on, and led by our Teachers? When as Chriſt himſelf hath told you aforehand, That <hi>if the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the ditch.</hi> No, you ſhall then curſe your King and your God, even your Pope, whom you have taken to be ſo to yourſelves, and followed him into thoſe evils that are excluded out of the Kingdom of God. Or will you think to ſay, We did what we did in a good intent? Will that excuſe? Whenas you are admoniſhed, <hi>not to do evil, that good may come thereof,</hi> and that admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is left upon record alſo. Will you ſay, We knew it not? Then ſee your blindneſs, ſee how your Leaders have kept you in blindneſs, leſt you ſhould ſee and know the truth and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your ſelves from under their yoke. What hath God given you reaſon and underſtanding for? Is it that you ſhould throw it away, or lay it aſide, or be led as a Horſe or Dog is, wholly by the will of another? Wherein then do you differ from Bruits? Do you not hereby manifeſt your ſelves to be thoſe ſtaves and ſouls of men mentioned to be in <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev. 18.13.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37495:11"/>I do not ſpeak theſe things ſo plainly to you to vilifie you, or in a way of deſpiſing of you, but to open your eyes, that you may ſee where you are, even at the pits brink, and that you may retreat before it be too late, and may obey that voice from Heaven which calls out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of ſuch confuſion of wickedneſs and abominations, as you are admoniſhed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>And I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> Her plagues will follow her ſins, therefore beware and take warning: You your ſelves cannot but know what abominations be in her, what whoredoms, and murders, and lyes, and perjury, and ſuch like, all counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and indulged by him that is King over your Conſciences, the Pope. So that I ſay, he walks not in the ſteps of that faith of our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> he is not of him, but of <hi>Apollyon,</hi> the Deſtroyer, the Murderer, and ſo is cut off from being of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s ſeed, and conſequently from being related to Chriſt, as his Vicar, or to <hi>Peter,</hi> as his Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>And for you his Diſciples or Followers, it's no marvel that you run on to ſuch horrid abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, beyond the very Infidels and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage people of the World, who know nothing of Chriſt, ſince you throw away your own reaſon, and give up your ſelves as ſlaves, to be led (as Horſes) and acted by thoſe, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37495:12"/>teach you to outface Conſcience, and to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare the checks and ſcruples thereof, and even to ſtrive againſt the principles of good nature and humanity, (as I am perſwaded ſome of you muſt do) who alſo to quiet your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, make you believe, That a Pardon or Indulgence from the Pope will clear all.</p>
            <p>Oh, the execrable wickedneſs that your Leaders prompt you on unto! Lying, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, Perjury, Plots, Treaſons, Murthers, Maſſacres, to be Truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, and what not! Will you not hereby in the end (beſides the juſt judgement of God againſt ſuch things) bring your ſelves alſo into that <hi>Odium</hi> with men, that no Man or Nation will truſt any thing you ſay or ſwear, or confide in any Truce that you can make with them, and ſo make your ſelves fit to be ſpewed out of the Earth? Ponder theſe things, I beſeech you, and do not ſtubbornly deſtroy yourſelves, but exerciſe reaſon as men, and hearken to the checks of your Conſciences, if they be not ſeared, and caſt away lying, and ſpeak truth, that you may be believed; and take heed of ſighting againſt God, whoſe hand you may ſee is againſt your deſigns of wickedneſs and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and learn to be inoffenſive, and without blame in the World, as the true Diſciples and Believers in Chriſt were, and ſtill are to this day. I have a little digreſſed for your ſakes, who are led as captives by this Man of ſin, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37495:12"/>inſtigator to Murthers and Maſſacres, that you might be convinced that he walks not himſelf, nor leads you on to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s faith, and ſo you ſhould beware of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Argument now againſt the Pope, I take from this Scripture, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. where the Apoſtle ſpeaking of a falling away, and the revealing of the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition, he deſcribes him thus, <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, ſo that he as God ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he is God.</hi> Hence I argue thus:</p>
            <p>If the Pope be found in this ſtate of the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition, then he is none of God's Vice-gerent, or Chriſt's Vicar, or <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor:</p>
            <p>But he is in the ſame ſtate or condition with this Man of Sin, here ſpoken of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is none of God's Vice-gerent, or Chriſt's Vicar, or <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>For the clear demonſtration of this, that the Pope is in the ſame ſtate with this Man of Sin here ſpoken of, we need go no further than this Chapter, and the Pope's anſwering of it, as the impreſſion of a Seal anſwers the Seal. There be two expreſſions here which ſhew, that this Man of Sin muſt be within the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity, but fallen from the life of it: For his riſe muſt be from a falling away,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37495:13"/>which in the Apoſtle's language, ſignifies a falling from Chriſt, the life and power of Chriſtianity, though they retain the Name of Chriſtians. Then the other expreſſion is, <hi>that he ſits in the Temple of God;</hi> he doth not flee from an outward profeſſion of the Worſhip of God, but makes that his Seat or Throne; which alſo diſtinguiſhes him from all Secular Powers. So that you ſee, he muſt be as to outward ſhew a Chriſtian, and worſhipper of God; and in that he is exalted and hath his Throne there, there he ſits: And from hence it is, that the Pope (who is one with him) arrogates to himſelf ſuch Titles, as import a near Relation to Chriſt, and his holy Apoſtles. Theſe things thus far are clearly fulfilled in him; he is fallen away from the life and power of Chriſtianity, from the innocency thereof, to the height of wickedneſs, as by his life, and actions, or works, make appear; and yet he retains the Name of a Chriſtian, and will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be a Worſhipper of God, and hath his Seat in his Temple, where his worſhip is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
            <p>Then further. This Man of Sin is ſaid to <hi>appoſe and exalt himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped.</hi> Magiſtrates in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture are ſometime called Gods; <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods, but ye ſhall die like men.</hi> And again, <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty, he judgeth among the Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82. Now this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37495:13"/>Man of Sin, and ſo the Pope, is exalted above all that's called God, above all Magiſtrates, Judges, Kings, Emperors. I think none will deny this, it is ſo well known in the World, ſince that the Pope hath taken upon him to crown them with his foot, and make them wait attendance at his gate, and to diſcharge Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their obedience to their Princes, and to depoſe whom he pleaſes, and give the Crown to whom he pleaſes. Here's oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enough contained alſo in this his Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while he deals thus with Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe three Marks or Diſcoveries of the Man of Sin, are fully found in the Pope. He is riſen up in the fallen ſtate; being fallen from the life of Chriſtianity; from a merciful ſpirit, to a cruel bloody ſpirit; from a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpirit, to a deceitful treacherous ſpirit; from ſpeaking truth, to ſpeak lyes in hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; from humility, to the higheſt exaltation of pride that a man can be at in this world. For this laſt, it's evident enough, for he is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above all; and for the reſt, that's alſo manifeſt by his Diſciples; for what he teaches his Diſciples to do or be, he muſt be that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Thus he is in the fallen ſtate, yet he ſits in the Temple of God, he profeſſes worſhip to him.</p>
            <p>Now let us take notice of ſome other expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in this place; He is called <hi>that Man of Sin,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37495:14"/>and Son of Perdition.</hi> For the Man of Sin, can we find the Pope worthy of that denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? I wonder who can look upon him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, (notwithſtanding his great Title of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi>) when we find him to be a Patron, nouriſher and cheriſher of the moſt inhumane Practices that are in the World; witneſs the Cruelties and barbarous Actions of his people, in ſeeking to deſtroy Nations, and their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, to overturn Governments, by Plots of darkneſs, and open butcherly Maſſacres, without any pity or mercy to Age or Sex. Witneſs alſo his cruel Inquiſitions, which are places invented for tormenting them, that will not ſtoop to his yoke; ſuch Engines as Chriſt Jeſus never appointed or countenanced, but was againſt all ſuch mercileſs tortures. Witneſs alſo his encouraging of his Children to take Oathes or Teſts, that they may not be diſcovered, and ſo reſtrained from doing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and from carrying on his helliſh deſigns, promiſing them pardon aforehand, for any falſe Oathes or Perjury, ſo it be for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his Church. Shall we not count him a Man of Sin, who walks thus fully in the ſteps of him, who was a murderer and a lyar from the beginning? I deſire to know where we ſhall find one that outſtrips him. And for that word, <hi>The Son of Perdition,</hi> this alſo is not amiſs applied to the Pope; for it ſignifies <hi>a Deſtroyer,</hi> who is alſo appointed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37495:14"/>and it bears the ſame ſence with <hi>Apollyou,</hi> Rev. 9.11. <hi>Who is King over them that have power to hurt men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another word alſo that hints ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to us, for further diſcovery of this Man of Sin; namely, that the Day of Chriſt ſhall not be, till the Man of Sin be revealed. This implies, that he ſhall be ſo hidden in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, under the profeſſion or pretence of his worſhip, that he ſhall not be ſeen to be what he is till God reveal him. And this alſo is very applicable to the Pope; for not only Nations, but their Kings alſo, have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with him: But now God hath in a great meaſure revealed him to be what he is; and he hath revealed him by the ſame means, whereby Chriſt Jeſus reveals falſe Prophets, and whereby he teaches us to know them, even by his works; ſo that his own works diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what he is. And as the Apoſtle makes this a diſcovery of evil men and ſeducers, <hi>that they ſhall grow worſe and worſe,</hi> ſo it is with the Pope, and his train of Murderers, they have grown worſe and worſe. Formerly they would bring men before their Courts, and there let them have free liberty to plead and argue for their Religion; but of later years nothing will ſatiate their cruelty, but quick diſpatch, and ridding them out of the way by ſpeedy Maſſacres. Thus now you ſee how fully theſe Diſcoveries of the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition, are found in the Pope.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37495:15"/>
            <p>Now put all theſe together, and let the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Papiſts ſee, where they will find one that anſwers all theſe Characters and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, as the Pope doth.</p>
            <p>A Man ſprung up under the profeſſion of Chriſt, but fallen away from him, into the very dregs of wickedneſs, oppoſing, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting, and murthering the innocent, who do him no harm.</p>
            <p>A Man that ſits in the Temple of God, whereby he is diſtinguiſhed from all Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, who have their Seat or Throne in the Civil Government.</p>
            <p>A Man exalting himſelf above all Magiſtrates and Principalities.</p>
            <p>And yet a Man of ſuch eminent note for ſin, that if I may not ſay he is deſervedly called, <hi>That Man of Sin,</hi> yet I may ſay, He is deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly reputed to be of that Man of Sin.</p>
            <p>A Son of Perdition, as <hi>Judas</hi> was, who is for deſtroying, ſtabbing, ſtrangling, poyſoning, murthering, maſſacring, and ſo for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>For the righteous Judge will give to every one according to his deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Man hidden from the vulgar Eye, under pretence of his Holineſs, until the Lord hath revealed him, being now manifeſt by his own wicked Practices; <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Find all theſe concurring in one Man, and exhibit him as repreſenting the Man here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37495:15"/>of, that Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition. Where you will find ſuch another beſides the Pope, I know not. This I am certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of, that your Pope is ſuch a one: He ſits in the Temple of God, challenging the Power over all in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, yea, and over Civil Governments too: He is a Man of Sin, a promoter and inſtigater of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sins, Murders, Lying, Perjury, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He is a Son of Perdition, if deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the innocent make one ſuch, as it did <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das:</hi> He is exalted above all that's called God, above all Principalities and Magiſtrates: He is a Man ſprung up under the profeſſion of Chriſt's Name, but is fallen away from him and his Doctrine, and turned an oppoſer. Therefore untill his Champions can find out another like him, in whom all theſe Characters may concur, let them reſt upon him.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>I do not queſtion but ſome will ſay, That</hi> Simon Magus <hi>was ſuch a one, and this Scripture was fulfilled in him, and ſo ſome have underſtood it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I Anſwer, It's true enough, that much of it was fulfilled in him; and therefore well might ſome of the Ancients think, that he and his followers were fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the great Antichriſt: Surely they were ingrafted into the ſame ſpirit with the Pope, becauſe they both have had the ſame carnal and earthly thought of the gift of God, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37495:16"/>That it might be purchaſed with money, as I have ſhewed. But then conſider, that if <hi>Simon Magus</hi> fulfilled this Scripture, in exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf over the Conſciences of many, as if he were above all, (although he never arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at that height that the Pope is got to) then the Pope, in exalting himſelf over all Principalities and Dominions, Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, not only in opinion, but in real Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of depoſing and ſetting up Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, he fulfils it much more For this height, I ſay, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> never came to: Therefore if <hi>Simon</hi> was a Son of Perdition, what is the Pope, who walks ſo much after his ſteps, yea in actual exaltation above him, in bloodſhed and murders, and burning and maſſacring, far beyond him? If they who lived near the primitive Ages, (who ſaw not this Son of Perdition as yet appearing in their time) thought <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or <hi>Marcus Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinianus,</hi> or any other, or all of the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> as one Body, to be that Son of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Great Antichriſt, they might well be excuſed in thinking ſo. But we, who have ſeen the Riſe, and of later years the Diſcovery, of this great Man of Sin, for us to turn off this Scripture from him, by limitting it to them, that never came to ſo great exaltation over all, I think in us it would argue great blindneſs. For though that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make men think him a God, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37495:16"/>many were deceived with him, yet he never got into the Saddle, to ride over all by his Power, as the Pope doth: And therefore after the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of thoſe men, the Ancients ſtill looked for another to appear as the Great Antichriſt. For when the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> began to affect the Title of univerſal Biſhop, others ſaid, <hi>He that ſhall affect the Title of univerſal Biſhop, is a fore-runner of Antichriſt:</hi> He that ſhall but affect it, was counted a fore-runner; therefore they lookt for another to riſe beſides <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or any that were gone before. And if affecting of that Title diſcovered a fore-runner, what muſt he be then that obtains the Title and Power of univerſal Biſhop? And that Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> that quickly ſucceeded <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, namely, <hi>Boniface,</hi> he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, and it was of <hi>Phocas,</hi> a wicked Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, that he obtained it; of whom it was ſaid, <hi>Deteriorem alium inveniri potuiſſe nullum,</hi> that a wickeder could not be found. He gave the Precedency to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and granted to <hi>Boniface,</hi> that it ſhould be called <hi>Caput omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> the Head of all the Churches. And then the Biſhop of it began to be the Head of all the Biſhops; contrary to the Command of Chriſt, who forbad that thing in expreſs words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25, 26, 27. <hi>It ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> ſaith he, when the Mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> Sons would have had her Sons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above the reſt. Therefore Chriſt Jeſus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37495:17"/>never gave this Greatneſs to the Pope over all, ſeeing he forbad it; but it was obtained of wicked <hi>Phocas,</hi> about the year 607. after the Nativity of Chriſt. For till that time the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was not exalted ſo very high, though he was high enough; but after this they grew by little and little ſo high, that they got above the Emperors themſelves. Then was fulfilled this Scripture which I have quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>He exalted himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped.</hi> And ſo now he is become the head of that <hi>great myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> which began to work in the Apoſtle's days, but was letted by the Heathen Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and therefore till that which letted, (being an enemy alſo) was taken out of the way, it could not riſe to its height: For the perfecuting Emperors letted, by keeping down the very outward formality and name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as much as they could; under which name and outward profeſſion, the myſtery of iniquity was to ariſe, after there was a falling away from the life and power of godlineſs. Now the Name of Chriſtianity becoming fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and the Nature of it loſt in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the greateſt abominations of the World, (Lying, Perjury, Ambition, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Superſtition and Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under that profeſſion, with pretence to promote it, and yet quite contrary to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it; this is the myſtery of iniquity.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37495:17"/>And of this myſtery the Pope ſtands in the Head: For where can one find the like Spirit of Lyes and Slanders? of Perjury, which they think they ſalve up with equivocations, and mental reſerves; of Ambition, as in the Pope and his retinue; of Murther, by poyſonings, treacheries, maſſacres; of Superſtition and Idolatry, in falling down before Images and Pictures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I might name many more groſs abominations, all indulged by the Pope their Father and Patron, Vicar (not to Chriſt, but) to him, that was a lyar and murtherer from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>If any one here object and ſay, That theſe and ſuch like wickedneſſes are practiſed among others, as well as under him, Look among the Proteſtants, and you ſhall ſee Murthers, Adulteries, Thefts, Robbing, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Lying,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are frequent among them, as well as under the Pope's Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer, Theſe and ſuch like ſins are too frequent among them, for which the Lord may chaſtiſe them, as alſo he hath done. But yet obſerve how great a difference here is: The Proteſtants by ſuch evils, bring themſelves under the danger of Penalties by their Laws; The Papiſts can act the greateſt wickedneſſes, under hopes of indulgence, and memorable reward of honour among them; ſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do that in danger, and are diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, where the Papiſts are countenanced
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37495:18"/>in the ſame evils. Again, It is the looſer ſort of Proteſtants that do ſuch things; but the Leaders and principal Men among the Papiſts, (from the Pope to the loweſt Graduate) are chief Incendiaries therein. Again, The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do ſuch things againſt the Principles of their Religion; but the Papiſts do them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the wicked Principles of their Church, that is, from iniquity eſtabliſhed by a Law; and if Satan rule any where, ſure it's there, where he hath got iniquity and murther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into a Law, and ſo under a mantle of Piety, to eſcape the cenſure of the purblind Eye. So that the Papiſts Church is become a very Spring of wickedneſs, through their principles, and leading men, who with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, counſel and contrivance, inſtigate their people to the moſt inhumane wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make them believe it's good ſervice done to God and his Church.</p>
            <p>Other Arguments might be produced againſt the Pope, to manifeſt him to be none of Chriſt's Vicar, or <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor; but I reſt in theſe, as ſufficient teſtimony againſt him: Seeing he is one with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in that evil thought of his heart, That the gift of God may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with money: And ſecondly, Becauſe he is not of the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo not of the ſeed of Chriſt, but one that walks in the ſteps of him that was a murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning: And thirdly, Becauſe he walks pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37495:18"/>with that Man of Sin, that Son of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or deſtruction, who exalts himſelf above all that's called God, and yet ſits in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, as if he were God, laying his own Impoſitions upon the Conſciences of men, thereby bearing ſhew of God among them, and over them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come now to the next Principle, which is this, That the Pope is infallible: But theſe things foregoing, being manifeſtly proved againſt him, by his own practice, quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn his Infallibility. For who will ſay that he is infallible, who is guilty of that ſin, which excluded <hi>Simon Magus</hi> from having any part or lot in diſpenſing the ſpiritual gifts of God, and which diſcovered him to be in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of iniquity? Who will ſay that he is infallible, who walks not in the ſteps of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s faith, but in his ſteps who was a murtherer from the beginning? Who will ſay that he is infallible, that exalts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all that's called God, or that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, who ſits in the Temple of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf that he is God, and yet is called, That Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition? How can the Popes be infallible, when the makers of them are ſo fallible, that they have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made two at a time, who have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed excommunicating one the other, as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander tertius,</hi> and <hi>Victor quartus</hi> did, about the year 1159. We may well ſay of them, as it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37495:19"/>was formerly ſaid of Images and their makers, <hi>They that make them are like unto them.</hi> Was that poyſoning Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, who poyſoned <hi>Joannem Michaelem,</hi> a Cardinal of <hi>Rome,</hi> and afterwards attempting to poyſon Cardinal <hi>Adrian,</hi> his familiar friend, with a cup of poyſon at a Banquet, was by the juſt hand of God poyſoned himſelf with the ſame; for the cups being miſtaken by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that cup which was appointed by him, to be given to <hi>Adrian,</hi> was given to himſelf, and ſo he died therewith? This was about the year 1503. as Chronicles tell us. Will you ſay, this Murderer was infallible?</p>
            <p>But not to expatiate too far in this, it being ſo groſs a thing to conceit that ſuch men are infallible, I proceed to the next Principle, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Pope hath power to pardon ſins. And here as I ſaid of Infallibility, ſo I may ſay of this: If <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> if the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therous <hi>Jews,</hi> if the Man of Sin, that's exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above all, have power to pardon ſins, then may we grant the ſame power to the Pope, but not elſe; for all theſe conditions are his, as hath been ſhewed. But if the Pope have all thoſe ſins lye at his door, that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his order, or inſtigation, or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of them; if he lye under the weight of them all, and be found guilty of them all, let him firſt repent and pray to God, that if it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37495:19"/>be poſſible, his own ſins may be forgiven him. <hi>David</hi> was charged with the death of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> becauſe he ordered and contrived it, and this one man's blood lay heavy upon him, and the ſword was never to depart from his houſe therefore, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.9, 10. Now how many Murders are committed by the Pope! What multitudes of innocent Souls have been ſlain by the Cruelties of Popes, in the barbarous maſſacring of many Thouſands, whoſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood cryes to Heaven for vengeance! For all the blood ſhed by his approbation, and ſuggeſtion, and inſtigation, and indulgence, will lye as a mighty Mountain upon him, and his Confederates who promote ſuch things. Let him firſt get from under the guilt and weight of his own ſins, before he pretend to pardon others. Will any man think, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> who had betrayed the Lord of Life, had power to remit ſins? No ſurely, none are ſo deſtitute of underſtanding. Now if Chriſt our Lord will look upon that which is done to one of the leaſt of them, which believe in him, as a thing done to himſelf, then how often will the Pope be found guilty of killing the Lord of Life in his little ones, who believe in him! The innocent blood of multitudes will riſe up in witneſs againſt him, being ſhed under his patronage. How many thouſands in <hi>Ireland!</hi> How many thouſands in <hi>France!</hi> How many thouſands in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and other places, have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37495:20"/>been ſlain, under the myſtery of iniquity, wherein he is Head, being King over them that have power to hurt men, and might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain ſuch Inſolencies and Cruelties, if he did diſallow thereof! Therefore all theſe, beſides the ſecret Murders and Conſpiracies done by his Indulgences, and beſides all the hidden works of darkneſs done in his cruel Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will all preſs upon him. And yet this Man, whoſe Sins and Cruelties, and unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Maſſacres reach to Heaven, he muſt be the Man to forgive men their ſins! Oh the blindneſs and beſotted condition of men whom the Lord hath given up to ſtrong deluſion! I beſeech you let us underſtand, who they are that are given up to ſtrong deluſion to believe a lye, if they be not that train that follows the Pope, and depends upon him for the pardon of their ſins. For the ſtrong deluſions are to come upon them that follow the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition, who exalts himſelf above all that's called God, and who ſits in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, as the Pope doth. And ſo you may find theſe deluded ones ſpoken of, as the train of that exalted Man of Sin in the ſame Chapter with him, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>But the Pope pretends to have power to pardon ſins, becauſe Chriſt gave that power to his Apoſtles; for he boaſts of his Succeſſion to them, eſpecially to <hi>Peter.</hi> But I aver, that he that is departed and fallen away from the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37495:20"/>Apoſtles Spirit and Doctrine, is no true Su<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſor to them, nor hath that power which they had. The Apoſtles were innocent, holy, humble men of heart, not ſeeking the glory of this World, as the Pope doth; not exerciſing dominion over mens Faith and Conſcience, as the Pope doth; nor lording it over God's He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, as the Pope doth; but were enſamples of piety and holineſs to the Flock of Chriſt. But the Pope walks contrary to their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to their Doctrine, being a devouring Wolf, where he cannot exerciſe dominion over mens ſpirits. He indeed arrogates to himſelf the title of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> but is far from the life of it, being a ring-leader into wickedneſs, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, maſſacres, perjury, diſſimulation, and wicked fraud, encouraging his Children to take Teſts or Oaths, ſo that they may lurk among us like Foxes, under Sheeps cloathing, until they can ſeize upon their prey. Is not here plainly a departing and falling away from the upright and innocent ſpirit, and wholeſom doctrine of the Apoſtles? When will your eyes be opened, you that are his Subjects and Slaves? When will you be ſenſible and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, what manner of Holineſs you have ſet before you to follow! I pray you conſider, what is it above and beyond theſe wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that he ſhall live in, who is ſuch a Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition? See if you can find out groſſer abominations among all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37495:21"/>Chriſtianity, for which thoſe titles may be put upon any man more juſtly. So then, ſeeing he is thus departed and fallen away from the Apoſtles ſpirit and doctrine, who will truſt to him for the remitting of their ſins, who have any good underſtanding or ſound reaſon left in them, and are not given up to ſtrong deluſion to believe a lye?</p>
            <p n="4">4. I proceed to a fourth Principle of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof the Pope is Head, is the true Church of Chriſt, and all that depart from them are Hereticks.</p>
            <p>That there was once a true Church, and a precious Church of Chriſt at <hi>Rome</hi> I grant, while they followed the Doctrine and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Life of Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles: But ſince they are fallen therefrom, into the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and lying treacherous ſpirit, they are become degenerate, and thereby cut themſelves off, as a Branch withered is cut off from the Vine.</p>
            <p>But here by the way, before I proceed any further, I deſire to be rightly underſtood, that the bent of my Diſcourſe is not againſt thoſe that are ſimple-hearted, and harmleſs among them, and honeſt according to their knowledg; but it is againſt the ruling and leading part, (who lead the reſt into evil) theſe are fallen away from Chriſt, and hold others in bondage, and keep them in captivity, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37495:21"/>were kept captives in <hi>Babylon</hi> of old. So there is a people that God calls his people in <hi>Babylon</hi> the great, the Mother of Harlots, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Earth: For ſaith the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> which words were inſignificant, if he had not a people in the midſt of <hi>Babylon.</hi> This being premiſed, which I deſire may be minded all along. I ſhall now for the finding out of the truth or falſhood of this 4th. Principle, put the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (that is, the ruling leading part, and the ruled part, from the Pope to his meaneſt Miniſter or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, who are ſpirited to teach, or actively to put in practice the deſtructive principles of their Church) be the only true Church of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Now for the readier finding out of the truth or falſhood in this Queſtion, I ſhall ſet another by it, which may run parallel with it, to give light to it; namely,</p>
            <p>Whether a people teaching, or by principles practiſing lying, perjury or falſe ſwearing, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and diſſimulation, Plots and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to deſtroy others, aſſaſſinations, ſecret murders, and open maſſacres, and other ſuch like abominations, and all this with conſent and approbation of their Church: Whether ſuch a people be the only true Church of Chriſt, and all that withdraw from them be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37495:22"/>
            <p>Thus the Queſtion is truly ſtated concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make it manifeſt; and being thus ſtated, I think I may leave the deciding of it to the meaneſt capacity, where there is any grain of honeſty left in their hearts towards Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Head of his Church: for certainly none will ſay, that ſuch a Church is the only true Church of Chriſt, and all others Hereticks, except they have ſold themſelves to ſpeak wickedly.</p>
            <p>Now that the Pope and his <hi>Romaniſts</hi> are ſuch a people, they themſelves prove by matter of fact; and by their actions they ſufficiently declare it to this preſent Age, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained for its own ſecurity to uſe the beſt means it can, to preſerve it ſelf from their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinations, ſtabbings, ſtranglings, ſinothering of their perſons, burning of their Houſes and Cities, and from their bloody hands, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs maſſacres.</p>
            <p>The Church of Chriſt in the Apoſtles days <hi>was the pillar and ground of truth,</hi> upholding and holding forth truth in the World, by teaching it, and by living in it, and ſo by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a juſt and innocent harmleſs life among men, ſo that they were of no danger to others among whom they lived. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is come to that, that ſhe is become the pillar and ground of lyes and ſlanders, of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, falſe accuſations, truce-breaking,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37495:22"/>hypocriſie, to ſeem one thing and be another to deny or hide their own Principles for wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ends; ſhe is ſo far fallen from an innocent harmleſs life, that ſhe is become the pillar and ground of Plots and wicked deſigns, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive the blowing up of Parliaments, the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of Nations, the deſtruction of Kings and Rulers, the maſſacring of multitudes, and butcherly murthering of thouſands of innocent people, that do them no harm. This is the Pope's <hi>Roman</hi> Church. And here we may ſtay our ſelves, and wonder with great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>John</hi> did when he <hi>ſaw the Woman drunken with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 17.6.</p>
            <p>This is ſhe that would be counted the only true Church of Chriſt, and holy Church, and mother Church, and brands all for Hereticks that abhor her abominations. Well might the Apoſtle wonder with great admiration, when in viſion he was ſhewed by the Angel, that ſuch a degenerate bloody people ſhould riſe up under the Name of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But is not this ſhe in whom (as it was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told) there was to be a falling away, to make way for the revealing of the Man of Sin? And ſo ſhe is become Mother indeed, but a bloody Mother, not holy Mother; what if we ſay, <hi>Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth,</hi> according as the great Whore is called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37495:23"/>
            <p>Whether the preſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof I ſpeak, be that very great Whore, ſpoken of in that Chapter or not, I refer it to further judgement; but this is plain, that many if not all of thoſe Characters whereby the great Whore is diſcovered, do meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> It will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be amiſs, or beſide the mark, to view ſome or moſt of them a little, as they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in that 17th. Chapter of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Verſe ſhe is called by the Angel, <hi>The great Whore that ſitteth upon many waters. Come hither</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>John) and I will ſhew thee the judgement of the great Whore that ſitteth upon many waters:</hi> And what theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are he expounds to <hi>John,</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>The waters which thou ſaweſt where the Whore ſitteth, are Peoples and Multitudes, and Nations and Tongues,</hi> which ſhews the large Dominion that the great Whore ſhall have; which well enough anſwers the ſtate and greatneſs of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which calls her ſelf Catholick, for her Dominion hath reached far and near. But as for the title of <hi>great Whore,</hi> how doth that any way anſwer to <hi>Rome</hi>'s condition? What ground is there for that title in her? This is worthy of conſideration. Therefore conſider, That a Woman that's married to a Husband, and proſtitutes her ſelf to another man, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Whore. And ſo by way of ſimilitude,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37495:23"/>the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were often charged with whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, becauſe they being a people owned by the Lord, and as it were married to him, yet went a whoring after their own inventions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.39. They went after <hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhteroth,</hi> and the Gods of the Heathens, and did not keep loyal to the Lord and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. This was imputed to them for whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The like thing being done by a people profeſſing themſelves to be married to Chriſt, as his Church, is alſo counted and called whoredom in them, becauſe they are not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and loyal to him, but proſtitute themſelves to other Inventions. This is ſpiritual whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Now where is there a people that are run out into ſo many Inventions of their own, as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is run out into? Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that have no ground at all either from the Doctrine or Practice of Chriſt, or any of his Apoſtles. Where have they ground for their daily mumbling over ſo many Prayers, ſo many <hi>Pater-Noſters,</hi> ſo many <hi>Ave-Maries,</hi> &amp;c. that they need Beads to number them by as they ſay them, and as if God were delighted with Lip-labour? Where have they ground to forbid Marriages to their Prieſts? Where have they ground to forbid Fleſh-meat as a caſe of Conſcience, on ſuch and ſuch days? Where have they ground for their Idol, the Maſs? for Invocation of Saints and Angels? Where have they ground for carrying about their Hoſt or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37495:24"/>Sacrifice, and making all do obeiſance to it, and worſhip it? Where have they ground for their idolizing the Croſs, and the Pictures of the holy Servants of God, falling down and praying before them, if not to them? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God will avenge his holy Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets upon them, for thus abuſing them, ſo contrary to that ſpirit that was in them, who could not endure that men ſhould fall down to their perſons, while they were upon Earth, much leſs now to their Images. In theſe and many ſuch like things the Pope's Church have run out, after their own Inventions. And this is whoredom againſt Chriſt, who was faithful in all his houſe, (that is, in his Church) as <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his, to teach them the whole counſel of God. Beſides all this, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath taken off her love from him, who is the great Friend of Mankind, and would have us ſo as he is, and ſhe hath placed it upon him, who is the great Enemy of Mankind, and follows his ſteps. For they have ſhut out that Spirit in which Chriſt comes, and makes his abode with his people, and whereby he forms his own Nature in them, and makes them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, humble, lowly, meek, merciful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and inſtead of that, they have let into their boſom the Spirit of the wicked one, whoſe works Chriſt came to deſtroy, and ſo by that Spirit they have the nature of him that was a murtherer and lyar from the beginning, formed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37495:24"/>in them, and ſo uphold the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, which Chriſt came to deſtroy in man. What greater whoredom from Chriſt than this?</p>
            <p>Now ſhe that outſtrips all others in ſuch like whoredoms, ſhe is the greateſt Whore againſt Chriſt, if ſhe profeſs his Name. And how ſully the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> falls under theſe things, I let others judge, and paſs on to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcoveries.</p>
            <p>Verſe 2. It's ſaid, <hi>With whom the Kings of the earth have committed fornication: And the Inhabiters of the earth have been made drunk with the wine of her fornication.</hi> This great Whore hath had power over the Kings of the earth, to bring them into the ſame ſtate of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication or whoredom with her ſelf, even to fall down and proſtitute themſelves to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and Traditions, and Idolatries, and ſo to partake of her Spirit. Let the Reader apply it; as alſo what follows, <hi>And the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of the earth have been made drunk with the wine of her fornication.</hi> She hath mingled a cup of her own Inventions and ſuperſtitious Idolatries, and ſo ſweetned it to the palate of earthly-ſpirited people, that they have drunk it down with delight like wine; but it hath intoxicated them, and made them drunken, ſo that like drunken men, without any rule over themſelves, they are for killing and ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and like ſavage beaſts, for puſhing down,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37495:25"/>and trampling upon all that ſhall withſtand their drunken humours, and ſenſleſs imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſuperſtitions, and they need but a watch-word from the Pope to ſet them on.</p>
            <p>Verſe 3. Another mark of the great Whore is opened: <hi>And he carried me away into the wilderneſs in the ſpirit, and I ſaw the woman ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon a ſcarlet coloured beaſt, ſull of names of blaſphemy, having ſeven heads, and ten horns.</hi> This Verſe, with the Angel's interpretation of it, will give us much light in the matter in hand: Therefore mind the Angel's interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Ver.</hi> 18. He tells <hi>John</hi> what that <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> is, <hi>The woman which thou ſaweſt is that great City, which ruleth (or hath a kingdom) over the Kings of the earth:</hi> So that you ſee this woman which is the great Whore, is a <hi>great ruling City, reigning over Kings.</hi> Then add to this the Angel's interpretation of the <hi>ſeven heads,</hi> Ver. 9. <hi>The ſeven heads are ſeven moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains upon which the woman ſitteth.</hi> So then thus far is plain, That the great Whore is a great ruling City, that reigns over the Kings of the earth, and is ſituated upon ſeven moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains. This ſo fully points out <hi>Rome,</hi> that their own Writers cannot deny it; for it is famous in all Nations for its ſituation upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven mountains or hills, which are theſe, <hi>viz. Mons Palatinus, Quirinalis, Aventinus, Caelius, Viminalis, Aeſquilinus, Capitolinus.</hi> Hence this City is called <hi>Septiceps,</hi> and <hi>Septicollis.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37495:25"/>that is, it hath ſeven heads, or ſeven hills Therefore <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeaks thus of it,</p>
            <q>Sed quae de ſeptem totum circumſpicit Orbem Montibus, imperii Roma Deum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> locus.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> which from her ſeven mountains views round the World, is the place of the Empire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's one opening of the ſeven heads, they are ſeven hills. The Angel gives it alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opening, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>And there are ſeven Kings, five are fallen, and one is, and the other is not yet come,</hi> which alſo ſtill further points out <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe ſeven Kings are ſeven Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; as ſome obſerve,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brightman;</hi> Rev. 17.10.</note> and five of theſe were fallen when <hi>John</hi> wrote the <hi>Revelations,</hi> and one then was, and another was not yet come at that time, which they thus interpret; <hi>Rome</hi> from its riſe or firſt original had theſe Heads: 1. Kings. 2. Conſuls. 3. Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. 4. Decemviri. 5. Tribunes; and theſe five were then fallen when <hi>John</hi> writ the <hi>Revelations.</hi> 6. Emperors, and that was the then preſent Government. And the 7th. was not yet come, which was by Popes. Thus both theſe opinions of the ſeven heads, meeting together ſo patly upon <hi>Rome,</hi> do ſtill confirm that to be the place of the chief reſidence of the great Whore, where ſhe ſitteth or is ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Some indeed take theſe ſeven Kings to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37495:26"/>be ſeven particular Emperors, and in that they vary, yet they meet in this, that they belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Rome;</hi> but in my underſtanding the firſt is moſt apt, and ſo Learned <hi>Brightman</hi> takes it, quoting, The Hiſtory of <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> for thoſe ſeveral Governments of <hi>Rome,</hi> until the Emperors, for he lived and writ in the firſt Century after Chriſt. But I place not much weight upon this, which may admit of dubious diſputation, but paſs on to other things.</p>
            <p>Again, It's ſaid in this ſame Verſe, that this <hi>Woman or great Whore ſitteth upon a ſcarlet coloured Beaſt.</hi> Beaſt is uſed in Scripture for <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.3, 17. <hi>Theſe great beaſts which thou ſaw are four Kings,</hi> or four Governments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now this beaſt which the Woman ſits upon, is ſaid to be <hi>ſcarlet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured,</hi> the colour of blood; ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is born up upon a bloody power, being upheld by bloody Cruelties, Inquiſitions, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Maſſacres; ſo that her ſins are as <hi>ſcarlet,</hi> wherewith ſhe is clothed: This is true enough of <hi>Rome.</hi> Or if we take this <hi>ſcarlet colour</hi> to ſet forth the ſplendor, magnificence, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the beaſt, or power that upholds the great Whore, this alſo is anſwered by <hi>Rome</hi>'s Equipage and Pomp.</p>
            <p>So put theſe together now: <hi>Scarlet coloured beaſt</hi> relates to that potent and bloody power that upholds the Whore: And <hi>great Whore</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37495:26"/>relates to Religion or Worſhip, and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of her Spirit, which is degenerated and adulterated with traditions and ſuperſtitions, and inventions of men: And the <hi>ſeven heads</hi> or <hi>mountains</hi> relate to her outward ſituation, or chief place of her reſidence, which the <hi>ſeven Kings</hi> or ſeven ſorts of Government alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, the Angel thereby pointing as with a finger, where to find her chief ſeat outwardly in the World.</p>
            <p>This beaſt in whom the power reſides, is alſo further deſcribed hereby, that it is <hi>full of Names of blaſphemy.</hi> To bring this home to <hi>Rome,</hi> this I ſay, That the Names of <hi>Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Holineſs, God's Vice-gerent, Chriſt's Vicar upon Earth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> Peter<hi>'s Succeſſor, Holy Church, Holy Mother, Mother Church, Abbots,</hi> (which ſignifies Fathers) <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> (which ſignifies Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus</hi>) and many other ſuch like Names and Titles, whereby men would ſhew themſelves eminent Servants of God and of Chriſt, nearly related to him. I ſay, theſe and ſuch like Names and Titles, being put upon moſt unholy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men, upon ſuperſtitious and idolatrous Worſhippers, upon bloody and inhumane Butchers, and ſlaughterers of men, upon ſuch as are teachers and animaters of lying and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, and ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie, upon truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of men to forſwear or perjure themſelves,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37495:27"/>under a cloak of Equivocation, inſtigaters of acters of Maſſacres, of Plots and Conſpiracies againſt Rulers and Nations, upon ſuch perſons as know theſe abominations aforehand to be ſins, and yet (having their Conſciences ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as with a hot Iron) will preſumptuouſly encourage men thereunto, or in defiance of Conſcience will ruſh into ſuch ſins, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Pope's Pardon. I ſay, ſuch Names and Titles upon ſuch perſons, or ſuch a people, is high blaſphemy againſt God, againſt Chriſt, and againſt his holy Servants, to whom they challenge Succeſſion; becauſe ſuch Titles of ſo near relation, render the God of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as a Patron to all ungodlineſs; they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſt as a generater and nouriſher of a brood of wicked people; they render Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity as a Nurſery of more than heatheniſh ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities, and inhumane abominations; they render Chriſt Jeſus, and <hi>Peter,</hi> as Teachers of wicked Plots and Conſpiracies. What can tend more to blaſpheme, that is, to defame that holy Name of God and of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are called? What can more blaſt the Fame (as the word Blaſphemy imports) of that innocent Lamb of God, and of his holy Apoſtles, by whom the profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was planted in the Earth? Well may the <hi>Jews, Turks, Infidels,</hi> abhor the Name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, looking upon it through the corrupt lives, and deceitful and ſavage actions of thoſe,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37495:27"/>that by ſuch Names and Titles profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to be ſo great Maſters of that profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the chief upholders of it. Thus the Name of God and of Chriſt is greatly blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, by the ruling Party of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, who dignifie themſelves with ſuch Names and Titles, ſo nearly relating to Chriſt, and yet live in ſuch abominations, as are ſo abhorring to his Nature.</p>
            <p>Again, This ſcarlet coloured beaſt on which the Whore ſits, is ſaid to have <hi>ten horns,</hi> that's expounded by the Angel to be <hi>ten Kings,</hi> ver. 12. And theſe muſt agree <hi>to give their kingdom unto the beaſt, until</hi> (an appointed time, that is, until) <hi>the words of God ſhall be fulfilled,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>And then they ſhall hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked.</hi> She hath reigned over the Kings of the Earth, and they have committed fornication with her; but God will put it into their hearts at laſt to hate the Whore, and make her deſolate; and good cauſe, when there is no fidelity to be found in her, except they be abſolute ſlaves to her, to do what ſhe will have them to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Thus this 3d. Verſe, together with the Angel's interpretation of it, doth ſo fully point at <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſeven-headed, or <hi>ſeven-hilled City,</hi> that the Popiſh Writers have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it to be <hi>Rome;</hi> only they frame this eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, (which ſtands need to be anſwered,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37495:28"/>before I paſs from it) <hi>viz.</hi> That this great Whore is not <hi>Rome</hi> preſent, but Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, <hi>Rome</hi> under the Government of the perſecuting Emperors, (who were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great) who in their time perſecuted the Chriſtians, and ſhed much blood: Which thing, ſay they, put <hi>John</hi> to great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, as is expreſt <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>And I ſaw the woman drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus; and when I ſaw her, I wondred with great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This, they ſay, was to ſee ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian blood ſhed by the perſecuting Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But, I pray you, what great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, or new admiration, could that put <hi>John</hi> to, to ſee open Enemies of Chriſtians drunk with their blood? Or what new thing was this to <hi>John,</hi> who was a companion in tribulation, with thoſe that ſuffered perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thoſe times, which he had ſeen before he writ this Book of the <hi>Reuelations?</hi> This could not procure ſuch new admiration, to make him wonder ſo much; but the ground of ſo great admiration lay here, To ſee a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (in viſion) to riſe up under that Name, that was then perſecuted, and under a great profeſſion of Chriſtianity, to have them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to him to be <hi>drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> while they ſo highly profeſſed <hi>Jeſus;</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37495:28"/>here was ground indeed of aſtoniſhment to <hi>John.</hi> But it's a weak and ſilly thing to turn this off from <hi>Rome</hi> preſent, to <hi>Rome</hi> heathen, under the perſecuting Emperors, as ſome of no ſmall Note do, whom at preſent I forbear to name. Suppoſe any of us had lived in the days of <hi>John,</hi> and had ſeen ſuch perſecutions as he had ſeen, and had been a companion in the ſame tribulation, under open profeſſed Enemies, would this be ſuch a matter of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to us, to have it repreſented to us over again in viſion? No, the frequency of a thing takes away the wondring at it, eſpecially with ſo great admiration. But to ſee a new thing, ſo ſtrange a thing, ſo contrary to the nature of the thing: In plainer words, to ſee Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians drunk with the blood of Chriſtians, to ſee ſo high profeſſing Chriſtians, who would honour almoſt every thing that appertained to Chriſt; honour his Mother, honour his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, honour his very Sepulchre, and the very Croſs upon which he was crucified, yea, the very images of a Croſs for his ſake, if I may not ſay adore them: A people that ſhould keep days in memorial of the Birth, of the Suffering, of the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt; keep days in memorial of his holy Apoſtles, and ſing forth their praiſes in their ſolemn Aſſemblies and publick Worſhips, and magnifie themſelves as the only Church of Chriſt, and count all others who joyn not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37495:29"/>with them in theſe things to be Hereticks: To have ſuch a people repreſented as drunk with the blood of Chriſtians, <hi>drunken with the blood of Saints, and of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> (a thing ſo contrary to what they bear a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of) here was matter of wonder indeed, to cauſe <hi>John</hi> to wonder with great admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is expreſſed, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. And this now apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agrees with the title of the <hi>great Whore,</hi> which title the perſecuting Emperors did not ſo fitly bear, ſeeing they never owned Chriſt as their Head and Husband, nor themſelves to be his Spouſe. But <hi>Rome</hi> that now is, doth challenge this near relation to him, and yet doth theſe things againſt thoſe that profeſs him, as well as her ſelf.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how fully the Spirit of the Lord doth diſcover the ſtate of degenerate <hi>Rome,</hi> by what hath already been ſignified to us: And I might here paſs on to other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; but becauſe they are ſo highly exalted in this conceit, and it is ſo rooted a Principle among them, that they are the only true Church of Chriſt, I ſhall deſire the Reader's patience, to view alſo what further diſcovery is left us upon record, in the two next following Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this 17th. Chap. <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>ver</hi> 4. and 5.</p>
            <p>Ver. 4. <hi>And the woman was arayed in purple and ſcarlet colour, and decked with gold, and precious ſtones and pearls,</hi> that is, with all the glory of this World, with which bait the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37495:29"/>Devil would have catched Chriſt himſelf, but could not. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſwallowed down the bait, and for the glory of this World hath ſtooped to his terms, to bow down to him, and let in his Spirit, who was a lyar and murtherer from the beginning, and ſo ſhe hath her reward, the pomp and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this World. And ſhe holds forth alſo a golden cup to the Nations, to make them drink of the ſame cup of fornication with her, as it follows in this Verſe; <hi>Having a golden cup in her hand, full of abominations, and filthineſs of her fornication.</hi> This aptly ſets forth the <hi>Worſhip of the great Whore,</hi> and the wine wherewith ſhe makes the Nations drunk. This wine is the wine of her fornication, and it's in her <hi>Cup, which Cup is in her hand,</hi> and beautiful to look at, being golden, or guilded with gold. She carries the Cup of her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in her hand; it's external or outward for a ſhew, not internal and in the ſpirit; it lyes in that which her own hand hath formed, and carved out to her ſelf, according to her own devices. And it is always ready, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and bundled up for any one in Orders, even the vileſt and wickedeſt perſon among them to carry in his hand, and offer up. And it hath a fine golden outſide to look upon, to pleaſe the eye; her worſhip is ſumptuous and glorious enough outwardly to the eye; and ſhe hath alſo guilded it with all the daintieſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37495:30"/>expreſſions that ſhe could pick out of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to pleaſe the ear; and compoſed Songs, and Anthems, and Hymns, and prepared Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and muſical Inſtruments, and Quires of Singers to accompany them, to elevate the minds of people, as if they were wrapt up in a heavenly melody for a while. But look with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cup, and what's there? There's Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Superſtition, Will-worſhip, Idolatry, falling down before Images, and Pictures, and Crucifixes, worſhipping of Saints and Angels, which God never commanded, nor they ever ſuffered men to do to them, but forbad them. They come not behind <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in their worſhip, when he cauſed all to fall down and worſhip the Image which he had ſet up, when they heard the ſound of the Cornet, Flute, Harp, Sackbut, Pſaltery, Dulcimer, and all kinds of Muſick; nor much behind him for Fire and Faggor, to devour thoſe that will not worſhip with them. We read but of one Furnace that he cauſed to be heated, to burn diſſenters in; but they have burnt multitudes of diſſenters, who would not conſent to their worſhip, witneſs <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and other places in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days. Add hereunto the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Murthers done otherways, by Inquiſitions, and bloody Maſſacres, her unſatiable blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſtineſs, and blood-guiltineſs. So that you ſee, although the Cup of <hi>Rome</hi>'s worſhip be a golden Cup to look at, yet within it's full of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37495:30"/>filthineſs of her fornication, it's full of dead mens bones, and all uncleanneſs, like the paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchres of the <hi>Phariſees. Iſrael</hi>'s wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which was of God's own appointment, became an abomination to him, (ſo that his ſoul hated it) for theſe two things, (which <hi>Rome</hi> is eminently guilty of) one was, <hi>Becauſe their hands were full of blood,</hi> Iſa. 1.13, 14, 15. The other was, <hi>Becauſe they had choſen their own ways, and their ſoul delighted in their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> Iſa. 66.3. Now for <hi>Rome</hi>'s wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, it's of her own forming, not of God's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and for blood, her hands are fuller of that than ever <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s was; and for ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious inventions, <hi>Iſrael</hi> cannot compare with her. Therefore her worſhip muſt needs be more deteſtable and abominable in the ſight of the Lord, than <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s was; being alſo aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated hereby, that whereas <hi>Iſrael</hi> was but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der types and ſhadows, as under a Schoolmaſter; but ſhe lives in the days of greater light, under the miniſtration of the ſecond Covenant, or new Covenant, which far excels the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in the glory of its light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. So that for her now with bloody hands, and with deceitful diſſembling hearts, to approach to worſhip the Lord, this muſt needs be an abomination. Judge in your ſelves, I deſire you, ye of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, what acceptance this can have with the Lord; for a people that plots and contrives the ſubverſion of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37495:31"/>and ſticks not to poiſon, or ſtab, or murder thoſe, that they fear may hinder their wicked deſigns, who barbarouſly maſſacre people more merciful than themſelves, who are manifeſted thereby to partake more of the heavenly nature than they: For a people that ſets up to themſelves Stocks and Stones, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Pictures in abundance, and falls down before them, and bows themſelves to the work of their own hands, and prays to them that are no Gods, nor preſent in all places with them to hear their prayers; a people that turn away in their hearts from the living God, and think to make Men and Angels their Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; for ſuch a people to approach before the Lord, and ſing forth their Anthems and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs unto God. Judge ye if this worſhip be not abominable, and like the painted Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, which appear beautiful outward, but within are full of dead mens bones and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yea, and full of dead mens blood too, <hi>which cryes to the Lord under the Altar, How long Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet <hi>Rome</hi> would paint over all theſe abominations, to blind the eyes of men, that ſhe may ſeem holy in the practice of all theſe things. She will tell you, that all theſe that ſhe kills, are Hereticks, and it's no ſin to kill them. She will tell you, that ſhe doth not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37495:31"/>worſhip Pictures and Images, (though ſhe bow down to them) but ſhe doth it in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to God; and ſuch like ſhifts and miſts ſhe caſts over her actions, to blind the carnal eye, and leave it in a miſt. And therefore how fitly doth the Spirit of God meet with her jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling evaſions, and fixes this as one of the marks of the great Whore upon her forehead, as a Name written, <hi>viz. Myſtery,</hi> as it follows in the next Verſe, which comes now to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>Ver. 5. <hi>And upon her forehead was a name written, Myſtery, Babylon the great, the Mothes of harlots, and abominations of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Name that the Spirit of God fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es upon the forehead of the great Whore, <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</hi> She commits Whoredom and Idolatry in a <hi>myſtery;</hi> ſhe ſheds innocent blood in abundance, and yet in a <hi>myſtery.</hi> She would not be thought to be an Idolatreſs, nor to commit Whoredom, nor to be a Murderer; ſhe would juggle you out of a belief of that which your eye ſees, and your ears ſufficiently hear of her; here is <hi>myſtery</hi> indeed, but it is the <hi>myſtery</hi> of iniquity, <hi>not the myſtery</hi> of <hi>plain-hearted godlineſs.</hi> And this Name is ſet in ſuch a place, that it's eaſie to read it; it's ſet where ſhe cannot hide it, if ſhe do but ſhew her face, it ſtands upon her forehead. The Front of all her Zeal carries Blood and Idolatry written in it, but yet vailed, and you
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37495:32"/>muſt not believe it to be ſo. Though you ſhould ſee her proſtrate her ſelf before her Idols, you muſt not take her to be an Idolatreſs; though you ſhould be attempted to be ſlain by her hands, and though you ſhould ſee many maſſacred round about you, yet you muſt not take her to be a Murderer; and though you ſhould hear her Children lye to your face, and prove themſelves lyars by their actions, yet you muſt not take this to be lying; yea, though they forſwear and perjure themſelves, yet you muſt not take this to be ſwearing out of truth: But you muſt take her to be a holy Mother, and pious worſhipper of God, under Idolatry; and a charitable tender-hearted Mother, in the midſt of Maſſacres; and a maintainer of truth by lyes, and perjury, and equivocations. She is an exact obſerver of the footſteps of her grand Champion, to walk thereafter, who though he be never ſo wicked, yet you muſt reverence his <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Another part of her Name is <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon the great.</hi> Names of many things under the Old Teſtament, are applied to like things under the New: As Prayers and Thankſgivings are ſometimes called <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Incenſe;</hi> New Covenant is called <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> are words ſometimes uſed to expreſs a like people by. There be three or four things remarkable in <hi>Rome,</hi> for which the Name
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37495:32"/>
               <hi>Babylon</hi> is put upon her: 1. Confuſion, and ſo the word <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Babel</hi> ſignifie; for <hi>Rome</hi> hath confounded all things under the New Covenant, with her traditions and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious inventions. 2. As <hi>Babylon</hi> of old was a place of great Idolatry, ſo alſo is <hi>Rome:</hi> Read but the Epiſtle of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> to them, that were captives to be carried to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and you may ſee how like they are; you may find it in the <hi>Apocrypha, Baruch</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Ye ſhall ſee in Babylon, gods of ſilver and of gold, and of wood, born upon ſhoulders, which cauſe the Nations to fear. Beware therefore that ye in no wiſe be like to ſtrangers, neither be ye afraid of them when ye ſee the multitude before them and behind them worſhipping them.</hi> Thus it is alſo in the ſtreets of the great City, <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Babylon, Rome,</hi> and among her Children, when they go about the ſtreets with their Hoſt, beſides all the reſt of their Idolatry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in their places of Worſhip, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. 3. As <hi>Babylon</hi> of old was exalted above all, and call'd <hi>Lady of Kingdoms,</hi> Iſa. 47.5. and the <hi>glory of Kingdoms,</hi> Iſa. 13.19. So <hi>Rome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts her ſelf in like manner, and calls her ſelf <hi>Mother Church,</hi> and <hi>Caput omnium Eccleſiarum,</hi> i.e. <hi>the Head of all the Churches,</hi> and ſits as Queen over all in her own exalted mind. But then 4 thly and laſtly, <hi>Rome</hi> is moſt fitly call'd <hi>Babylon,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſhe holds the ſeed of God in bondage and captivity.</hi> Whom ſhe leads captive
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37495:33"/>once, ſhe will hardly let them eſcape without danger of their lives, or cruel torments in her Inquiſitions; they muſt become perfect ſlaves to her Superſtitions, Will-worſhips and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. And what bondage is like to this? that people to whom God hath given reaſon and underſtanding, ſhall not make uſe of it, but lay it aſide, and ſubmit wholly to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings or rather wills of others, though it be againſt their own, and ſo be urged to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to that which is againſt the light in their own Conſciences: And this is the greateſt bondage and captivity of all; and therefore well may <hi>Rome</hi> be called <hi>Babylon the great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She is alſo called <hi>Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth.</hi> She brings forth Harlots, that is, ſuch Children as go a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with her after her Inventions. Thoſe that in tenderneſs of Conſcience, and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the words of Chriſt, (who ſaid, <hi>In vain do you worſhip me after the traditions of men</hi>) will not joyn with them in their inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted traditions and ſuperſtitions, ſuch ſhe owns not for her Children; ſhe will be no Mother or Nurſe to ſuch, but ſeeks to murder them in cold blood, as none of hers: ſhe will be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother of Harlots, that can proſtitute themſelves with her, to her Idolatries and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions; and if they can do that, it ſhall not break the band between them, although they be common Harlots in the vulgar ſence; but ſhe will remain their Mother.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37495:33"/>
            <p>She is alſo Mother of <hi>abominations in the earth.</hi> Not only Mother of abominations in Worſhip, and ſuperſtitious Inventions, but alſo Mother of abominations in the earth; abominations as to the civil life of men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſideration of worſhip; abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to men, as they are men living upon the earth. To manifeſt this, I ſhall quote one Scripture, and then her own actions will te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the truth of it againſt her: It is <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Theſe ſix things doth the Lord hate, yea, ſeven are abomination to him: A proud look, a lying tongue, hands that ſhed innocent blood, an heart that deviſeth wicked imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, feet that be ſwift in running to miſchief, a falſe witneſs that ſpeaketh lyes, and him that ſoweth diſcord among brethren.</hi> Now ſee and judge, if <hi>Rome</hi> be not <hi>Mother of theſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Who more lofty in ſpirit, than the Pope and his <hi>Romaniſts?</hi> Can any compare with him who exalts himſelf over all, makes his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals as Princes, his Biſhops and whole Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as great men, and makes his whole Train diſpiſe others, as Hereticks, not worthy to live in the earth? Here's a proud look indeed. And for a lying tongue, <hi>Rome</hi>'s Children are ſo pregnant with that, that one cannot tell how to believe either what they ſay, or what they ſwear. How miſerably were the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi> cheated by them, by fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and deep oaths, that they would ſecure
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37495:34"/>their Goods for them, (in the time of that bloody Maſſacre) and yet when they had got them into their hands, refuſed to reſtore them, yea, and afterwards murthered them? And ſo 3dly, They have hands that ſhed innocent blood, none like them for that. 4thly, An heart that deviſeth wicked imaginations. Whoſe hearts are ſo full of wicked imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Plots, Conſpiracies, and devices of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, as <hi>Rome</hi>'s Children? 5thly, Whoſe feet are ſwifter in running to miſchief than the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who in one brunt can cut off ſo many thouſands by Maſſacres, before they make an end? Their feet are ſpeedy to do miſchief, when they get but the opportunity. 6thly, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other abomination is <hi>a falſe witneſs that ſpeaketh Lyes.</hi> If we go no further than this year, how have they endeavoured to choak all true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports among us, with their lyes and falſhoods? Witneſs the falſe reports and lying ſtories that they gave forth, about the death of Worthy <hi>Godfrey,</hi> till the truth appeared by Evidence, and could no longer be hid. 7thly and laſtly, <hi>He that ſaweth diſcord among brethren,</hi> is alſo one of the abominations in the earth. This is one of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Principles, <hi>Divide &amp; impera,</hi> Divide and then command: Divide, what's that but ſowing of diſcord, deſtroying of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſetting one againſt another, that ſhe may fiſh in troubled waters? Whether ſhe made the former diviſion and diſcord between the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37495:34"/>late foregoing King, and the People, or no, I will not ſay; but if they did, it's but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Principle. Thus you ſee <hi>Rome</hi> is a fruitful <hi>Mother of abominations of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now you may alſo at leiſure view all theſe things over again, and ſee how pertinent all theſe Characters of the <hi>great Whore</hi> are to <hi>Rome;</hi> they fit her as a garment that ſits cloſe and compleat upon a man's back. And why then we ſhould be afraid to look upon her, as that great Whore here deſcribed by the Angel to <hi>John,</hi> I know no reaſon; eſpecially if we add that which follows in the 6th. Ver. of this 17th. Chap. <hi>viz. And I ſaw the Woman</hi> (that is, the great City ſeated on ſeven Hills) <hi>drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus: And when I ſaw her, I wondred with great admiration.</hi> But having ſpoken of this afore, and ſhewed that it muſt be <hi>Rome</hi> profeſſing Chriſtianity, and not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Rome,</hi> that cauſed this great admiration; I forbear to ſpeak more of it now.</p>
            <p>I ſay, till <hi>Rome</hi> ſhew the contrary to theſe Characters, by a better liſe and converſation, they will reſt upon her. And it's not by her poyſoning and ſtabbing, fire and faggot, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions and Maſſacres, that ſhe can clear her ſelf: No, that way confirms and fixes theſe marks more fully upon her; the more ſhe ſeeks to wipe off the ſtains of blood that are upon her, by ſuch means, the more and greater they ſtill appear.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37495:35"/>
            <p>And now for the deciding of the Queſtion in hand, which all that I have ſaid tends to: Let any that have any reaſon of their own to make uſe of, and any honeſty and faithfulneſs in their hearts towards God and Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, judge and determine the Queſtion; Whether this Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo guilty of theſe things, be the only true Church of Chriſt now, and all others that draw from her be Hereticks? I hope whoſoever conſiders theſe things, will eaſily be convinced, that the withdrawing from this Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth not make a man a Heretick. I alſo further af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That he is no Heretick that <hi>doth juſtly, loves mercy, and walks humbly with God,</hi> becauſe theſe are the weighty things which the Lord requires in man. He is no Heretick that abides in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and in the innocent life of Chriſtianity; but he is the Heretick that ſtrives againſt theſe things to overthrow them, to overthrow the Doctrine of Chriſt, to overthrow innocency, truth, juſt and upright walking, and mercy. <hi>In every Nation, he that fears God and works righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, is accepted of him,</hi> therefore cannot be a Heretick; but he that caſts the fear of God behind his back, and works the works of him that was a Lyar and Murderer from the beginning he is the Heretick, becauſe he hath choſen Inventions and falſe Doctrines of his own to follow, contrary to the Lord's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirings.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37495:35"/>Having done now with this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, wherewith they ſo magnifie themſelves, and would frighten others, I proceed to the next.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The 5th. Principle I named is this, <hi>That out of the Church is no ſalvation; Extra Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am non eſt ſalus,</hi> ſay they.</p>
            <p>This is to be underſtood of their Church: And that being ſufficiently laid open by their own practice, I think it needs no further evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to diſprove it, unleſs people will needs believe that there is no ſalvation but among blood-thirſty Murderers, and Lyars, and falſe Swearers, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>But obſerve the craft and cunning of this Principle, which <hi>Rome</hi> makes uſe of to her own advantage. Firſt, It ſerves as a Decoy to draw in the ſimple among them, under hopes that there they may find ſalvation. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, It ſerves as a Jaylor to keep them in, when they are in; for thereby they terrifie them, as if it were damnation to depart from their Church, yea, or to entertain thoughts, that others who are out of their Church can be ſaved; <hi>for out of the Church,</hi> ſay they, <hi>there is no ſalvation,</hi> and they would have you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is no true Church but theirs, and ſo out of their Church there is no ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This they would make men believe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by their fruits the Lord hath made them manifeſt to be a Nurſery of abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37495:36"/>
            <p>But put caſe that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were the only true viſible Church; or underſtand any other true viſible Church, any people whatſoever, gathered and conſtituted into a viſible body; yet even in ſuch a caſe, I do not ſee how it can hold true, that out of that Church there is no ſalvation. Let thoſe that are otherwiſe minded prove it; for my part, it is plain to me, according to the Scripture, <hi>That in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs, is accepted of him: And that God will render to every man according to his deeds; to them who by patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for glory, and honour, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi> (to them he will render) <hi>eternal life,</hi> Rom. 2.6, 7. And again upon this occaſion, when a Centurion (being a ſtranger as to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> which was then the Church) came to <hi>Jeſus</hi> to have his Servant healed of the Palſie, and deſired him but to <hi>ſpeak the word, and his Servant ſhould be healed;</hi> hereupon Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I have not found ſo great ſaith, no not in Iſrael.</hi> And then he adds further theſe words, <hi>And I ſay unto you, that many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and from the North, and from the South, and ſhall ſit down with Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of Heaven; but the Children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out into outer darkneſs,</hi> Mat. 8.11. Luk. 13.29. What ſignifies this, but that many Children of a viſible Church ſhall be caſt out, when as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37495:36"/>many others that appear not of it, ſhall come from all parts, and ſit down in the Kingdom of Heaven with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Another of their Principles is this, <hi>Fides non eſt ſervanda cum Haereticis,</hi> that is, <hi>Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks.</hi> If <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> had been under the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Doctrine, he would not have kept faith with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> when they obtained a league with <hi>Iſrael</hi> by craft: But he had a better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer than the Pope, and gave better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and therefore both he, and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> would not that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſhould periſh, becauſe of the league and peace made with them, and becauſe they had ſworn unto them, yea, although theſe <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were of the Nations that were to be rooted out. So great authority had an Oath and Covenant, and did ſo greatly oblige at that day, as you may read, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9. But the Pope, he can tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon all Solemn Oaths, Leagues and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants whatſoever, and break all bonds at pleaſure, yea, and all bounds of humanity, and ſolemn Engagements, when he pleaſes, if he do but ſay, They are Hereticks with whom the League is made. What is it that can bind him, or his Diſciples? Therefore in the end who will truſt the Papiſts, to make any league with them, or at leaſtwiſe depend upon that league with ſecurity, and not rather ſecure themſelves againſt them as well as they can?
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37495:37"/>Time was when an Oath or Covenant gave reſt to people; but now it can give none to people of another profeſſion, that have to deal with the Papiſts, becauſe faith is not to be kept with them, as they ſay: Thus they are fallen from the fidelity of mankind, to the deceitful tricks of Satan. Formerly men reſted in one another's friendſhip, and ceaſed from ſtrife and controverſie, and fear one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they had paſſed their Oath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was then an immutable thing among men, and ſo an Oath was the end of all ſtrife, as you may read it was ſo between <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 31. And the ſame immutability and weight that was in an Oath among good men, the ſame immutability and ſtedfaſtneſs Chriſt Jeſus did require in words under his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, <hi>Let your yea be yea, and nay be nay:</hi> But the Papiſts hold to neither of theſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to truth in Words, nor truth in Oaths. So that you may plainly ſee, that herein the Pope and his Children, and Confederates in Antichriſtianiſm, are faln away, not only from Chriſt's Doctrine, but alſo from the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of that firſt Miniſtration, which ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf.</hi> We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to put away Lying, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.25. But falſe Swearing and Covenant breaking is the height of Lying: <hi>Lye not one to another, ſeeing that you have put off the old man with his deeds,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9. But the Pope
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37495:37"/>teaches his Children to put on the old man and his deeds, and to give themſelves up to Lying, and falſe Swearing, and Covenant breaking; whereof many inſtances might be produced; take theſe two or three: About the year 1444. (if <hi>Bucholcer</hi> compute aright) when the <hi>Turke</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had confirmed a Truce between them, by ſolemn Oaths on both ſides, <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the Pope writ to Cardinal <hi>Julian</hi> thus, <hi>Nullum valere faedus quod ſe inconſulto cum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus Religionis percuſſum eſſet;</hi> that is, <hi>That no Covenant was of force, which was made with the enemies of Religion, without his advice.</hi> Whereupon the Truce was broken with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and they thought perfidiouſly to have ſurprized them; but the vigilant Turk <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi> was too nimble for them, and had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a great Army to meet them, which was done ſo ſuddenly, that it was firſt ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was heard of, which ſtruck great ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror into the Pope's Army; and after a great ſlaughter on both ſides, the <hi>Turks</hi> went away Conquerors, whereby providence would have taught them, That faith was to be kept with enemies, though enemies of Religion. And ſo <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> was convinced, before he was made Pope; for, ſaith he, ſpeaking of this War, <hi>Victores evadunt Turcae, qui juramenta non ſolum domeſticis fidei, ſed etiam hoſtibus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanda demonſtrant: The Turks go a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, who ſhew, that Oaths of fidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eye to be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37495:38"/>kept not only with the houſholds of faith, but alſo with enemies.</hi> Whether this <hi>Aeneas</hi> might condemn the ſame again afterwards or not, I know not; for he writ things before he was Pope, which he condemned after he was made Pope; whence this ſcoff was put upon him, <hi>Aeneas probavit, Pius damnavit; Aeneas ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it, but Pius condemned it,</hi> for he was call'd <hi>Pius ſecundus</hi> after he was made Pope: Sure there is a curſe of Error adheres to the Pope's Chair, and not a bleſſing of Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But to keep to the thing in hand: How treacherouſly was the Noble Admiral <hi>Coligni</hi> ſlain, and thrown out at a Window at <hi>Paris,</hi> contrary to promiſe, and Oaths of ſecurity! And at the ſame time many thouſands of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants murthered. <hi>Parry</hi> a Papiſt, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> though he had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times ſworn to be true to her, yet for all that ſought to kill her, <hi>Becauſe faith is not to be kept with Hereticks.</hi> You ſee how ſafe it is for Proteſtants to keep Papiſts about them; for ſuch murtherous actions is one of the Papiſts works of Supererogation, for which they me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to be canonized for Saints among the Pope's Catalogue. This Perfidiouſneſs of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> is ſo notoriouſly known among Proteſtant Nations, and eſpecially of late among our ſelves, that there needs no further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration thereof, than the treacherous concealed Murders of ſeveral among us very
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37495:38"/>lately, who, it's very probable, have been trappann'd, under fawning and fair pretences, into ſnares, where they have loſt their life, as Worthy <hi>Godfrey</hi> loft his.</p>
            <p>I am now come to the laſt Principle which I named, which is as the cloſe of theſe bloody Principles and Practices of the Papiſts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. That it is no ſin to kill a Heretick, or at leaſtwiſe it ſhall not be imputed to them as a ſin; but rather is a meritorious work to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Hereticks, whether they be Kings or People, Noble or Ignoble, ſo that it be for the advantage of their Church.</p>
            <p>This ſerves as a Spur to prick forward the Pope's Train to ſuch bloody work; eſpecially when they ſee ſuch as are moſt active therein, canonized for Saints, and ſo highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>I queſtion not but many of them may be ſpurred forward in themſelves, with the deſire of gain, to enrich themſelves in the ruine of others, and with other the like ſordid and earthly Conſiderations. But I let that paſs, and apply my ſelf to this Principle of theirs, as a Caſe of Conſcience only.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe they will not deny this Principle to be theirs: If they do, their practice will make them lyars; by their murtherous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wicked Plots and Deſigns againſt the Proteſtants to deſtroy them, together with their Honour that they put upon ſuch wicked practitioners.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:37495:39"/>
            <p>To overthrow this Principle of theirs, there is no need of much labour therein: For it ſo fully manifeſts it ſelf to be contrary to the Spirit of Chriſt, and end of his Coming, and alſo oppoſite to the Doctrine and Command of Chriſt, that every Boy that can read the Scriptures may eaſily perceive it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to its contrariety to the Spirit of Chriſt, and end of his Coming, he himſelf ſhews it plainly. When <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> out of their great reſpect and love to him, and zeal they had for him, would have called for fire down from Heaven, to conſume thoſe that did not receive him, <hi>He turned and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them, and ſaid, Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of: For the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave them,</hi> Luk. 9.54, 55, 56. What can be more plainly ſpoken to ſhew, that this way of deſtroying mens lives, for his ſake, or becauſe they do not receive him, is contrary to the Spirit of Chriſt, and end of his Coming. Therefore ſuppoſe that the Pope's Church were infallibly in the truth, (which yet is not granted, but admit ſo) and that the Proteſtants were moſt certainly in error, yet for them to deſtroy the Proteſtants upon that account, this is far worſe than <hi>James</hi>'s and <hi>John</hi>'s action; for they did but deſire, with ſubjection to Chriſt, to do what they would have done; but theſe, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting themſelves to Chriſt's words, kill and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37495:39"/>burn the Proteſtants, and deſtroy mens lives, out of a blind, incorrigible, furious zeal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they greatly aggravate their wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This Principle and Practice of theirs, is directly oppoſite to the Doctrine and Command of Chriſt, which he taught his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.24, &amp;c. where he firſt teaches the People by a Parable, and then gives his Diſciples the Interpretation of it. The Parable is of the Tares of the Field, which ſprang up among the good Seed. And the Servants of the Maſter of the Field came to him and ſaid, <hi>Sir, didſt not thou ſowe good ſeed in thy field? from whence then hath it tares? He ſaith unto them, An enemy hath done this. The ſervants ſaid unto him, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them up? But he ſaid, nay; leſt while ye gather up the tares, ye root up alſo the wheat with them. Let both grow together until the harveſt, and in the time of harveſt I will ſay to the reapers, Gather ye together firſt the tares, and bind them in bundles to burn them, but gather the wheat into my barn.</hi> This Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is as a Queſtion ſtated on purpoſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by Chriſt himſelf, to put an end to all ſuch thoughts or doubts, Whether the Children of the Kingdom, may root out the Children of the wicked One, out of the World. Mind therefore how Chriſt expounds his own Parable; and it is a preſumptuous wreſting of the truth of it, to divert it to any other ſence;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37495:40"/>for who knows the meaning of a Parable ſo well as he that gives it, eſpecially as the Lord that gave it. At the requeſt of his Diſciples, who ſaid, <hi>Declare unto us the Parable of the tares of the field,</hi> he opened it to them, <hi>ver.</hi> 37. and ſo forward. <hi>He anſwered and ſaid unto them, He that ſoweth the good ſeed is the Son of man; the field is the world, the good ſeed ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the children of the Kingdom; but the tares are the children of the wicked one; the enemy that ſowed them is the Devil; the harveſt is the end of the world; and the reapers are the Angels.</hi> Now read the Parable as Chriſt hath expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it: <hi>The Servants of Chriſt the Son of man</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover tares, (that is, <hi>Children of the wicked one</hi>) ſprung up in the field (<hi>the world</hi>) where Chriſt ſowed good ſeed (that is, <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Kingdom.</hi>) They ſtate this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Chriſt, and ask him, <hi>Wilt thou that we go and gather them up</hi> (or root them out?) here's the Queſtion: Now Chriſt's determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it follows, <hi>But he ſaid, nay;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all gives a reaſon why they ſhould not, <hi>leſt while ye gather up the tares, (the children of the wicked one) ye root up alſo with them the wheat (the children of the Kingdom.)</hi> Then he gives a poſitive Precept or Command, <hi>Let hoth grow together until the harveſt (the end of the world.)</hi> And to ſatisfie his Servants, and ſtay their minds from further enquiry, or doubt in this matter, he tells them upon whom he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37495:40"/>will put this work: <hi>In the time of harveſt (at the end of the world) I will ſay to the reapers, (the Angels) Gather ye together firſt the tares, (the children of the wicked one) and bind them in bundles to burn them, but gather the wheat, (the children of the Kingdom) into my barn.</hi> What can be more clearly expreſt to ſhew, That the Children of the Kingdom, are not to root up or deſtroy the Children of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one out of the World? But they are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by plainly commanded to let both grow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Field, (that is, in the World) until the end of the World. Now admit, (which yet is not granted) That the Papiſts were in very deed the Children of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that the Proteſtants were the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the wicked one, and peſtilent Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as they pleaſe to term them; yet you ſee what Rebels theſe Papiſts are againſt the Doctrine and Command of Chriſt, in ſeeking to root them out; and what incorrigible uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and intruders they are, who thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon that work, which Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſhall be the work of the Angels by his appointment.</p>
            <p>So now you may plainly ſee, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, as they are fallen from the Spirit of Chriſt, ſo alſo they are fallen from the Doctrine of Chriſt, into plain diſobedience, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt him. And therefore if any of them ſhall out of zeal ſeek to deſtroy Hereticks, you
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37495:41"/>ſee their zeal is but a blind zeal without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; they that do ſo, are ignorant of God, and of Chriſt, and his Doctrine; for that's the reaſon that Chriſt gives of a bloody zeal; <hi>Theſe things will they do unto you, becauſe they know neither the Father nor me.</hi> It may be they can talk high things of God and of Chriſt with their tongues, but I ſay they know him not; they know not the divine Nature, nor are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of it, and therefore are they of a bloody zeal. Let the Prieſts, Jeſuits, Monks, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, or Pope himſelf, ſcorn it as much as they will, yet, I ſay, ſuch know him not; bloody-minded men know not God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor Chriſt Jeſus; they have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his Spirit, being acted by him that was a Murderer from the beginning.</p>
            <p>I have now done with theſe their unſound and erroneous Principles, whereby they ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate their people, and harden their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to run on into miſchief: And I hope the error and wickedneſs of theſe Principles will be plain to the meaneſt capacities, by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of truth produced to diſprove them.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſet before you a few better Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, for them to meditate on, which will better abide the tryal, being according to plain Scripture, and which will bring more peace at the laſt, to thoſe that are found walking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them; whereby alſo you may take ſome Proſpect of the dangerous Paths of the Leaders of the Papiſts.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:37495:41"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave mens lives; not to deſtroy them, and therefore would not ſuffer his Diſciples to be deſtroyers,</hi> Luk. 9.56. From this Principle it's eaſie for any to draw this Inference, That therefore deſtroyers and murderers are not of him, but of their Father, that was a murderer from the beginning.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came a light into the world, that whoſoever believeth in him, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth him, ſhould not abide in darkneſs,</hi> Joh. 12.46. <hi>But ſhould have the light of life,</hi> Joh. 8.12. Hence you may ſafely infer, That he that keeps people in darkneſs, and makes them believe that Ignorance is the Mother of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth not walk in the ſteps of Chriſt, but oppoſes this end of his Coming, to enlighten the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the not knowing the Scripture, and power of God, is a cauſe of error, for ſo Chriſt taught,</hi> Mat. 22.29. Hence it's plain, That depriving people of the uſe of the Scriptures, which teſtifie of Chriſt, (the power of God) is not the way to keep them out of error, but to keep them in it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That Chriſt Jeſus our Lord came to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh truth in the Earth, and to extirpate falſhood not only in Oaths and Covenants, according to the firſt miniſtration, but even in every little word, without ſwearing; therefore he teacheth, Let your yea be yea, and your nay be nay,</hi> Mat. 5.37
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37495:42"/>This Inference eaſily follows hereupon, That they that ſpeak lyes in hypocrifie, do not give heed to him, and his Spirit, but to ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle witneſſeth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. And therefore Lyars are excluded the Kingdom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. and <hi>Gh.</hi> 22.15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That our Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus humbled himſelf, and became of no reputation, and we are bid to be like minded,</hi> Phil. 2.5, 6, 7. <hi>He was meek and lowly in heart, and bids us learn of him,</hi> Mat. 11.29. Hence we may take notice, That exalted Spirits, fierce and high-minded Spirits, who ſeek the greatneſs and glory of this World, are no good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to follow, becauſe they have not learned that of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That he that humbles himſelf as a little Child, the ſame is greateſt in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 18.4. Then he is not the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, that exalts himſelf above all, as the Pope doth. God beholds the proud afar off, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.6. Whoſoever ſhall exalt himſelf ſhall be abaſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.12.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That Chriſt Jeſus our Captain and Lord, came to ſet up a peaceable Kingdom, conſiſting of a people, peaceable, harmleſs and innocent in the World. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain, ſaith he,</hi> Iſa. 11.9. Then he came not to beget or bring forth a turbulent fort of Plotters, Contrivers, and Actors of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37495:42"/>miſchief and violence, ſo contrary to his own nature. Where will ſuch hurters and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers find place in all God's holy Mountain?</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>As ye would that men ſhould do unto you, ſo do ye unto them; this is Chriſt's Doctrine, and the ſum of the Law and the Prophets,</hi> Mat. 7.12. Ponder this you deſtructive Plotters, Jeſuits, Prieſts, Confeſſors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Would you have others ſeek your ruine? Would you have others to lye to you, to deceive you, till they could deſtroy you? Are your Conſciences ſo far ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or your Underſtandings blinded, that you are not able to judge aright in this caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your ſelves, and then concerning others? Or do you ſee theſe things, <hi>viz.</hi> that you do thoſe things, which you would not have done to you, and yet in defiance of Chriſt's Doctrine, will continue to go on in doing ſo? Conſider your ways, and take warning; you will find it hard kicking againſt the pricks. How far are you from doing as you would be done by, when as you uſe them deſpitefully that harm you not!</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The Miniſters of Chriſt, they uſed only ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual weapons, for the propagating of the Church of Chriſt: The weapons of our warfare are not carnal but</hi> yet <hi>mighty,</hi> (being ſpiritual) ſaith the Apoſtle; and ſo they were ſuch as reached the Underſtanding and Conſcience, to bring down high imaginations, and every thought, into obedience to Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. The
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37495:43"/>Pope's Miniſters ſeek to propagate their Church with carnal weapons, ſuch as cannot inform the Underſtanding and Conſcience; therefore they are altogether unlike the true Miniſters of the Goſpel in their way. In what rank of the Miniſters of Chriſt then will you appear, that uſe ſuch weapons for your work, when every man's work ſhall come to tryal?</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus ſets before us the example of our heavenly Father to follow, in doing good againſt evil, that we may be worthy to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted his Children,</hi> Mat. 5.44, 45. How far then are they from doing good againſt evil, that do evil to them that ſeek not their hurt! How ſhall we account them Children of our heavenly Father?</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>We are to follow men as they follow Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1. <hi>Becauſe he left us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21. Hence we may infer, That it's needful that men know the Scriptures, that they may be acquainted with the life and converſation of Chriſt, and ſo knowing his ſpirit and life, they may be able thereby to judge of the ſteps of thoſe they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; for otherwiſe how ſhall they judge of mers ſteps by his? Is not this the reaſon then, why you leaders of the Papiſts, keep your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the free uſe of the ſincere Scriptures of truth, that they being ignorant thereof, you may lead them as you pleaſe?</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:37495:43"/>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus is the Way, the Truth, and the Life; the faithful and true Witneſs, whoſe words were ſo eſtabliſhed in truth, that though Heaven and Earth paſs away, yet his words ſhall not paſs away,</hi> Mat. 24.35. <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo witneſſes, that <hi>the lip of truth ſhall be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever, but a lying tongue is but for a moment.</hi> How long then will your deceitful tongue bear you out, whoſe words are full of lying and ſlandering reports, and whoſe oaths are full of equivocation and mental reſerves; to make your tongue utter to the Underſtandings of men a falſe thing? Is this the lip of truth, that belyes the Mind? Is not ſpeech given for this end, to utter the Mind? Where have you any example, or precept, or conſent for this deceit, either from Chriſt, or any of his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers? Who then that would follow Chriſt, can follow you? Are not you to be turned away from, as perſons leading out of the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of him, that was and is the faithful and true Witneſs?</p>
            <p>I ſhall not multiply more: Theſe few Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, if men did live in them, (as they ought to do if they be Chriſtians) how peaceably, how ſecurely, how comfortably might they live together in the World, though of ſeveral perſwaſions in many points of outward obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations about Worſhip. But what peace, what ſecurity, what reſt can men have among thoſe who are bloody-minded, and deceitful, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37495:44"/>treacherous, giving themſelves up to ſpeak lyes in hypocriſie? who are among men, as Beaſts of prey among the Flocks? as Lions lurking in their dens, watching for the prey? If there be any room left in your hearts, ye <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> for conſideration of your ways, I entreat you, for your own good, ponder with your ſelves a little, and conſider your latter end, and the Judgement that will follow, when the impartial Judge will bring every thing to light, and render to every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deeds done in the body. What plea will you then have, when he ſhall ſay to evil doers, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not, ye workers of iniquity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wickedneſs now of the foregoing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Papiſts being laid open, and upon good grounds rejected, and ſome better Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, according to Scripture, ſet before them, yielding more peace among men, and in a man's own Conſcience alſo, and better hopes of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſs; I ſhall now touch a little their great Bulwarks or Props, whereby they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this their Kingdom of darkneſs, upon theſe rotten Principles: And they are theſe two principally, namely, <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Ignorance;</hi> and theſe are like two Arms, wherewith they hold faſt their Subjects.</p>
            <p>There be many other things accompanying theſe, as Lyes, Slanders, Defamations, ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of others, proud boaſting of their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37495:44"/>and of their Succeſſion, to thoſe whoſe lives and ſpirits they have quite deſerted, wreſtings of truth and true reports, making people believe falſhoods, falſe gloſſes put upon their own wicked actions and deſigns to do miſchief, and a great deal of ſuch like ſtuff they raiſe a miſt with, to blind peoples eyes. What a pudder did they lately make about the Death of that Worthy <hi>Godfrey,</hi> whom they moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly murthered in <hi>Somerſet-houſe?</hi> cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Cruelty every way, by turning it upon his own head, as if he kill'd himſelf, or as if he were kill'd by Robbers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But God infatuated them in the action, and made it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that neither he himſelf had done it, nor was he kill'd by Robbers; for they that rob by the High-ways, take away Money, not only Writings: And for killing himſelf, they could not make that hang together neither; for he could not fall upon his own Sword after he had broke his own Neck, and how could he break his own Neck after he had faln upon his Sword? or how could he do both at once, as ſome would have excuſed it? Yet theſe and ſuch like Forgeries, how did they fly about, and were backed with that confidence, that they dazled the minds of many, eſpecially of great perſons, among whom the Papiſts moſt converſed? Thus they manifeſt their Kingdom to be a Kingdom of <hi>Crnelty,</hi> backt with lyes and falſhoods, and other works of darkneſs.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37495:45"/>But Godd hath been pleaſed to force out the truth, of this bloody action, from ſome that were privy to it, and could relate the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, ſo that it's blazed upon the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tops, in ſpite of all their windings and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigs to hide it.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Cruelty,</hi> I ſay, accompanied with ſuch things as I have named, is one of their main guards or ſupports of their Religion. It is like a wall of fire round about them; ſo that if any among them ſhall but attempt to get out from them, what can they look for but Fire and Faggot, or a moſt helliſh Inquiſition, if they catch them? And what tortures and torments are acted there, may ſufficiently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright and terrifie ſuch as think of deſerting them. This <hi>Cruelty</hi> is innate to their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for finding themſelves defective of truth to uphold it, they make it up with cruelty, and with lyes, when they have done, to hide it. That horrid piece of Cruelty intended by the Gunpowder-Plot, and carried on ſo far as it went, by their Creatures; though thoſe Actors in that work of darkneſs be honoured by them at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet they would have you believe, that it was only a trick of State, ſo impudently ſhameleſs are they in forging lyes. They would alſo make you believe, that the <hi>Book of Martyrs</hi> is full of lyes, and no better than a Fable, becauſe it records the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Butcheries and Cruelties, which by them
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37495:45"/>were acted upon conſcientious people: And all the ground they have to belye it is from hence, that there was a miſtake or two in it, which <hi>Fox</hi> himſelf, who was the Compoſer of that Book, firſt diſcovered, having had ſome wrong information given him in thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. Thus they are not aſhamed to act Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clties, but are aſhamed to be apprehended therein; for indeed their actions are ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, that even humane nature may bluſh to be found guilty thereof. And yet they are fain to fly to this refuge of defence to uphold their Religion, and alſo for the propagating of it: For indeed to ſpeak properly, it is not the Kingdom of God and of Chriſt, (having truth for its foundation) which they uphold; but it's a Kingdom of pride, luxury, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, and debauchery, which wants a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in truth; therefore fly they to Cruelty for their ſupport. And their Cruelty ſo rings over the World, that all but themſelves and their ſlaves, dread to come under their power: For there is no mercy in them to old or young, male or female, to innocent Babes, or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with Child. Oh the tortures, and the invented devices of Cruelty, that they put people to in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſince our memory, in the year 1642. driving them into Rivers by droves, and keeping them therein from getting-forth till they were drowned! This was the eaſieſt death they put them to. Some they hanged,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37495:46"/>ſome they ript open, and let out their bowels, ſome they ſtarved to death, ſome they buried alive, ript up Women with Child, daſhed the heads of Infants againſt the ſtones, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtript Men and Women naked, and cauſed them to periſh with cold and hunger; many moſt beaſtly and barbarous tortures they put both Men and Women to. And this now is their way of defending and propagating their Religion, which their God, who was a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer from the beginning, acts them violently forward in.</p>
            <p>Time was when they were ſomething more moderate in their bloody ways, when they cited people into their Courts, and gave them a Tryal at their Laws, and ſuffered them to argue for their Religion: But now they are become violently ſavage, and bruitiſh beyond all humane modeſty; whereby we may take notice of two things: 1. That they are Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; and that we need not doubt of, becauſe they wax worſe and worſe, according to the Character which the Apoſtle gives of Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi> 2. We may hence alſo have ſtrong hopes, that they have but a ſhort time to reign and rage in the World; for therefore Satan is come down among them with great rage, knowing that he hath but a ſhort time. This their <hi>Cruelty</hi> now (and not Truth) is one
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37495:46"/>of the grand pillars, by which their Kingdom is upheld.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another pillar upon which their Irreligion (as I may call it) or Kingdom of Darkneſs ſtands, is <hi>Ignorance.</hi> They take away the Key of Knowledge from men, and keep them in blindneſs, that ſo they may be led by them as they pleaſe. And to colour this piece of policy, they would perſwade their people, that Ignorance is the Mother of Devotion, and that the Scriptures make men Hereticks; as ſome of them in the Maſſacre in <hi>Ireland</hi> got an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bible, and trampling upon it in the dirt, (as is informed) curſed it, ſaying, that that was the cauſe or ground of all the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and therefore it is a thing not to be born with, (by them) that any of their Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people (as they term them) ſhould have the Bible or Teſtament, except it be as they have corrupted it. So they keep them from that, that they may keep them in ignorance, and they keep them in ignorance, that they may rule them as they pleaſe, and the people being deluded by them, are willing to have it ſo; for they ſee not the Serpent's ſubtilty, that lyes hidden under that Maxime, That Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is the Mother of Devotion: It is indeed the Mother of Devotion, but to whom? Not to God, I teſtifie, but to the Pope, and his ſuperſtitious and idolatrous Worſhip: Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance keeps men devout to him, and his will-Worſhip;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37495:47"/>but Chriſt Jeſus came to raiſe up a people, that ſhould worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth; and his Spirit is the Spirit of a ſound mind, not a Spirit of blindneſs and ignorance. The devouteſt men upon Earth have always been a knowing underſtanding people, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job, Samuel, David,</hi> and the reſt of the Worthies renowned in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, yea, and the Son of God himſelf, who was filled with wiſdom and truth, who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſpent the night in prayer to God; and he that is born again, is in his meaſure renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in knowledge after his image. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9, 10. <hi>Lye not one to another, ſeeing that ye have put off the old man with his deeds, and have put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge after the image of him that created him.</hi> Mind this, that the new man is renewed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; he is not kept in darkneſs and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to make him devout to God. When <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Athens,</hi> and beheld their blind devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in their ignorance; to rectifie this their devotion, he endeavours to bring them to true knowledge, not to keep them ſtill in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; for that was his work, (as alſo the work of the reſt of the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt) <hi>to turn men from darkneſs to the light, and ſo from the power of Satan</hi> (whoſe Kingdom is in darkneſs) <hi>unto God,</hi> (who is light) <hi>that ſo they might receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and an inheritance among them which are
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37495:47"/>ſanctified by faith in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Act. 26.18 Now he that ſtops up the light from men, muſt needs be a Thief and a Robber, which comes to ſteal: 1. To ſteal away the hearts of men from Chriſt to himſelf, and from devotion to God to devotion to himſelf, to ſerve his own turn. And 2. he thereby robs people of their deliverance from the power of Satan, who rules in darkneſs, as God rules in light. And ſo 3. and conſequently, he robs people of receiving forgiveneſs of ſins, and inheritance among them that are ſanctified by faith in Chriſt Jeſus; for that's the end of turning men from darkneſs to light, and from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Satan to God, namely, that they may receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and inheritance among God's ſanctified ones. But this will not ſtand with the Intereſt of him, who ſeeks the glory and greatneſs of this World, and an uncontroulable Kingdom over all, without queſtioning what he doth; and therefore Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance muſt be the nouriſher of blind obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, which he blaſphemouſly calls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to God. And in this work now, though he ſeek to be as high as <hi>Lucifer,</hi> yet hath he made himſelf a ſlave to the Rulers of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this World, whoſe principal drudge he is, in labouring to keep men in darkneſs, where Satan's power is. We find in Scripture, that darkneſs is the periſhing ſtate, out of which God calls his people: <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Ye were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37495:48"/>darkneſs, but now are ye light in the Lord, walk as children of the light.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9. <hi>Ye are a choſen generation—that ye ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him, who hath called you out of darkneſs into his marvellous light.</hi> Col. 1.12, 13. <hi>Giving thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light, who hath delivered us from the power of darkneſs</hi>—And therefore to abide in darkneſs, and to abide in a periſhing ſtate, is all one in Scripture-language; as alſo to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of the Lord, is expreſſed by being <hi>caſt out into outer darkneſs.</hi> 1 Joh. 2.9, 10, 11. <hi>He that hateth his brother is in darkneſs, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, becauſe that darkneſs hath blinded his eyes:</hi> And Darkneſs is the place where there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12. and 22.13. Now then it is eaſie for any to judge, whoſe Miniſter he is that hides light from men, to keep them in the darkneſs, and whoſe work he doth: He is none of Chriſt's Miniſter, nor doth his work to promote his Kingdom, which is a Kingdom of light; but he doth the work of the Rulers of the darkneſs of this World, and his own work, to keep men in ſlavery to him, who ſeeks the glory of this World. And this now is one of the ſtratagems of the myſtery of iniquity, and one principal prop of Antichriſt's Kingdom, and a chief guard about the Pope, to let him ſleep at quiet.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:37495:48"/>
            <p>Thus the Sword or carnal Weapons of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Ignorance, and ſuch like means, are the props and guards of this Kingdom, which the Papiſts are Subjects to, and not the pure and uncorrupted Truth recorded in Scripture. And therefore that ſome of them may deliver themſelves from that myſtery of iniquity, (if the Lord pleaſe to open their eyes) is the end of my writing theſe things. And though ſome expreſſions in this Treatiſe may perhaps ſeem too harſh to ſome of them, yet having to deal with ſuch bad Principles, in perſons who pretend to be inveſted with authority and power derived from Chriſt, in the work of his Miniſtry, and in his ſervice, I could not uſe eaſier language than I have done.</p>
            <p>And as I have here manifeſted the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Principles of the Papiſts to be moſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and wicked, I ſay the ſame againſt the deſtructive zeal of any profeſſors of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, upon what Principles ſoever they go, and under what Name ſoever they ſtand; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affirm, <hi>That no deſtructive zeal is renewed after the image of him that hath created us, and made us new creatures; for as God ſent not his Son into the world to deſtroy, ſo he came not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, but a Saviour, to ſave mens lives.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would he not ſuffer <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to deſtroy, nor <hi>Peter,</hi> when he drew his Sword, and cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his Ear, but bid him put it up, and then heal'd the Ear again which he
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37495:49"/>had cut off; and hath left it upon record, that his Servants ſhall not go about that Work, to root out the tares out of the field, (that is, the World) that's a Work reſerved for the Angels at the end of the World.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now, for concluſion, leave a few Queries, for the Papiſts to ſatisfie their own Conſciences in, rather than to expect an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to them; and I deſire them to be impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial while they conſider them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Lord hath taken up an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Succeſſion again, ſince he laid aſide <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s natural Succeſſion?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether any be a true Succeſſor of <hi>Peter,</hi> or of the reſt of the Apoſtles, who doth not walk in the ſame Spirit and Doctrine?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether Chriſt hath ſubſtituted a Patron of Lying Perjury, Plots, Conſpiracies, Cruelty and Murders, to be his Vicar, to repreſent him upon Earth, and to be the Head of his Church, and an example to the Flock? And whether it be not great blaſphemy to affirm it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether he be a friend or an enemy to Chriſt, who oppoſes the main ends of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? As namely in theſe particulars: 1. In point of Enlightning. 2. In point of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. 3. In point of Worſhip. Firſt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt came to enlighten the World, and to bring them out of darkneſs; but the Popes ſtop the light, and keep men in darkneſs.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37495:49"/>Secondly, Chriſt came to raiſe up a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, inoffenſive, quiet, innocent people, and of them a Kingdom of Peace, where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould hurt nor deſtroy; but the Popes bring forth a people quite contrary, harmful, offenſive, unquiet, diſturbers of the Civil Peace, by Plots, Conſpiracies, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, Chriſt came to bring forth a people that ſhould worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth, ſuch as the Father ſeeks to worſhip him; but the Pope requires ſuch Worſhippers, as will ſtoop to his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and idolatrous Worſhips, after the Formality that he preſcribes, or elſe they muſt expect an Inquiſition, or ſome other uſage as bad. Now conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that thus oppoſes the Ends of Chriſt's Coming be not an Enemy?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether he that knoweth ſin afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and yet entices or encourages his Children into it, by promiſing them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and indempnity if they do it, doth not very aptly follow the ſteps of that old Serpent that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> who told her, <hi>Ye ſhall not die though ye eat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether thoſe <hi>Roman Caſuiſts</hi> do err, that ſay, It's no ſin to ſwear a falſhood, if they have a Reſerve in their mind to ſalve it with? Or it's the Pope that errs in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing Pardons for ſuch Oaths, ſo making them ſins? For Pardons are Relatives to Sins.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37495:50"/>
            <p n="7">7. Whether Equivocations and mental Reſerves will ſtand as a good plea for Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Perjury, at that day when the righteous Judge of all the World ſhall judge every man according to his deeds? And when a greater plea ſhall have no accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; as namely, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name? and in thy name have caſt out devils? and in thy name have done many wonderful works?</hi> But Chriſt ſhall ſay unto them, <hi>Depart from me, ye workers of iniquity,</hi> Mat. 7.22, 23.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether ever the true Chriſtian Church, or any members of it, ſtanding faithful, diſſembled their profeſſion, by denying, or ſwearing againſt their Principles in open words, to ſave themſelves thereby from men?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether that be not a denying of Chriſt before men, to deny that Truth, which he hath left us to profeſs and hold forth in the World? And whether he will not deny ſuch, and be aſhamed of them before his Father? You that think you are in the truth, and yet deny it, apply this to your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether they who dare not avouch their Religion and Principles before men, in truth and ſincerity, when called to it, have any Religion in them worth the owning?</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:37495:50"/>
            <p n="11">11. Whether a mercyleſs people or a more merciful people, be nearer to the true Church of Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether a people degenerated from the true, upright, humble, inoffenſive, pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable, quiet, ſincere, holy life of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and faln to Lying, Treachery, Plots, Murders, Maſſacres, and ſuch like evils, be the only true Church of Chriſt? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all others are Hereticks, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from their Communion? Let your Conſciences ſpeak, as it will do before the Tribunal of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether a people, that make the Times perillous, through their Plots, Aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinations, Murders, Treacheries, and ſuch like evil courſes, (although they ſhould retain a form of godlineſs in outward ſhew) be not ſuch as are to be turned away from, according as the Apoſtle admoniſhes? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whether a people full of violence, as the old World was, and as <hi>Sodom</hi> of old was; a people full of Slanders and Lyes, to hide their works of darkneſs, as if they were afraid that the World ſhould ſee their treacherous intents, before they put them in execution? Whether ſuch a people be not well-nigh ripe for deſtruction?</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:37495:51"/>
            <p>Theſe Queries I leave with you, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your Conſciences in, if there be any fear of God remaining in them; and let me entreat you not to deal deceitfully with your own Conſciences, which will be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt you at the great Day, when the Pope's Indulgences and Pardons will do you no good.</p>
            <p>As for Anſwer to me in theſe things, I cannot rationally expect any from the Scriptures of Truth, for they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to themſelves. I know the Pope and his <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have one Catholick or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Anſwer for all Objections, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Doubts, Oppoſitions, Queſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby to prevent diſcoveries of their weakneſs, or rather wickedneſs: And that any one may expect, that writes or ſpeaks againſt their myſtery of wickedneſs, and it's the ſame wherewith they have ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd <hi>Godfrey.</hi> For they are ſenſible that their Cauſe will not abide the light, and therefore they flee from that, to this work of darkneſs, to murder, which they back with Lyes and Slanders. And therefore let this be a Teſtimony to all that have any underſtanding, That they are Children of darkneſs, and not Children of the light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for it is the teſtimony of our Lord himſelf, That <hi>he that doth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37495:51"/>they are wrought in God: But every one that doth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> or made manifeſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>FOr the ſake of ſome honeſt-minded People' who perhaps may think that I too much limit the <hi>Myſtery of iniquity,</hi> or the <hi>Great Whore,</hi> or <hi>Babylon the great,</hi> in ſeeming to fix them to any particular People; to ſuch I give this Account in ſhort; That the <hi>Myſtery of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Great Whore,</hi> which carries that My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery written on her forehead, and <hi>Babylon the great,</hi> and ſuch like Titles, are not given in Scripture to the univerſal or general Kingdom of Satan, but to a limited Myſtery both as to time and place. For 1. That Myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity had not its riſe or beginning, till after the appearance of Chriſt in the fleſh; it began but to work in the Apoſtles days, but was not then revealed openly. 2. It was to follow or accompany a falling away from Chriſt, in life and power, though not in profeſſion. 3. It was letted for a time by an Enemy, namely, when Satan in his open hoſtility raged againſt Chriſtianity in the perſecuting Emperors, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37495:52"/>ſo by them letted or kept down the riſing of the Myſtery of iniquity, until that Enemy was taken out of the way. 4. It is alſo limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or bounded as to time of diſcovery, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and after that of rooting out; for the Kings of the Earth, who have given their power to the Beaſt, and ſo to the Whore, and ſo alſo to the Myſtery, (for they are all linked together in a Chain) they ſhall ſurvive or out-live it; for they <hi>ſhall hate the Whore, and eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire, and make her deſolate,</hi> Rev. 17.16. 5. Laſtly, It is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited as to place, thus far, That the chief Seat of it where it is to be found, is particularly deſcribed by the Angel, though its influence may extend far. And therefore it is not that general Dominion or Kingdom of Satan, which he hath had in wicked men from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and in all wicked men, and ſhall have every where among them until the end: But it is a certain circumſcribed Myſtery, limited both as to time and place of its chief Seat, though extended far for place, and long for time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:52"/>
            <head>Books Printed for a general Service.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BArclay</hi>'s Apology for the true Chriſtian Divinity, as it is held forth and preached by the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> being a full Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of their Principles, by Arguments deduced from Scripture and right Reaſon, and the Teſtimony of famous Authors, both Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Modern.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Barclay</hi>'s Apology for the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Divinity, vindicated from <hi>John Brown</hi>'s Examination, and pretended Confutation thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Barclay</hi>'s Epiſtle of Love and friendly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to the Ambaſſadors of ſeveral Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> met at <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> to conſult the Peace of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Fox</hi> and <hi>John Burneat,</hi> A <hi>New-England</hi> Fire-brand quenched, being an Anſwer to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Williams,</hi> of Providence in <hi>New-England,</hi> which he dedicateth to the King: As alſo an Anſwer to his Appendix, wherein are Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Ancient and Modern Authors, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Light, Scriptures, Rule, and the Soul of Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Shewen,</hi> The true Chriſtian's Faith and Experiences briefly declared, concerning God, Chriſt, the Spirit, the holy Scriptures, the Goſpel and Doctrines thereof, with a few words concerning Conſcience: To which is added a ſmall Treatiſe concerning evil Thoughts and Imaginations, and good Thoughts and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Meditations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s Quakeriſm no Popery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Keith,</hi> Immediate Revelation not ceaſed, or Jeſus Chriſt the Eternal Son of God revealed in Man, revealing the Knowledge of God: With an Appendix containing an Anſwer to ſome further Objections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Keith,</hi> The true Chriſt owned, as he is true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect God, and true and perfect Man; being an Anſwer to a Pamphlet called the <hi>Quakers,</hi> concerning the Man Chriſt, writ by a nameleſs Author, in Anſwer to a Book called, The Way caſt up, and the ſtumbling Block removed from before the feet of thoſe, who are ſeeking the way to <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> with their faces thitherward: By <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Keith,</hi> The way to the City of God deſcribed, or a plain Declaration, how any man may within the day of Viſitation given him of God, paſs out of the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, into the righteous ſtate, as alſo how he may go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the way of holineſs, and ſo be fitted for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stephen Smith,</hi> The true Light diſcovered to all who deſire to walk in the day; being a Collection of his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in a ſmall Volume. 8o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compendium trium Linguarum Latinae, Graecae &amp; He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braicae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Compendium or Abridgment of three Languages, the Latin, Greek and Hebrew, couched and exhibited in a ſhort and eaſie method, for the ſtudious and Chriſtian Youth</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37495:53"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
